<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An heavenly chariot layde open for transporting the new-borne babes of God, from time infected vvith sin, towards that æternitie in the which dwelleth righteousnesse. Made up of some rare pieces of that purest golde which is not to bee found but in that ritchest thesaurie of sacred scripture. By M. David Lindsey, ministerr of Christs Evangel at Leith.</title>
            <author>Lindsay, David, 1565?-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15683.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841106</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An heavenly chariot layde open for transporting the new-borne babes of God, from time infected vvith sin, towards that æternitie in the which dwelleth righteousnesse. Made up of some rare pieces of that purest golde which is not to bee found but in that ritchest thesaurie of sacred scripture. By M. David Lindsey, ministerr of Christs Evangel at Leith.</title>
                  <author>Lindsay, David, 1565?-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Raban, printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Sainct-Andrevves :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprinted in STC 15684.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15654 on UMI microfilm reel 579.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 15654.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5665:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5665:1"/>
            <p>AN HEAVENLY CHARIOT, Layde open for tranſporting the <hi>New-borne Babes of GOD,</hi> from time infected vvith Sin, towards that aeternitie in the which <hi>dwelleth Righteouſneſſe.</hi> Made up of ſome rare pieces of that pureſt Golde which is not to bee found but in that ritclieſt Theſaurie of Sacred Scripture. By M. DAVID LINDESEY, Miniſter of CHRISTS EVANGEL at LEITH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. XIII. VERS. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Here we haue no continuing Citie; but we ſeeke one to come.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COL. III. VERS. 1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If ye bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe thinges which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God. Set your affections on things which are aboue, &amp; not on things which are on the Earth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at Sainct-Andrevves, By Edward Raban, Printer to the Vniverſitie. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5665:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5665:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVELIE <hi>RELIGIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, AND</hi> Right Noble Ladie, LADIE ANNA KER, <hi>Ladie Balmerinoch,</hi> Grace, Mercie, and Peace, through IESVS CHRIST, our LORD, and onelie SAVIOVR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing in this laſt and moſt dead Age of the Worlde (Right Noble Ladie) there be not a few living (alace) not onelie under the blinding Darkneſſe, and corrupting Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of abominable Poperie; but alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſhining Lanterne of that ſaving Goſpel, which leadeth men directlie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes that bright morning Starre CHRIST IESVS, bleſſed for evermore: who holding (ah mee!) this Earth for their Home, doe never dreame that they muſt bee remooved from it: and ſo who cannot bee mooved ſo much as to beginne to thinke upon another Habitation; let bee to fit themſelues for it: not-with-ſtanding that None-ſparing Sworde of Death, ſlaying daylie, without reſpect of perſons, men of all Rankes, in everie place, may ſenſiblie cleare unto them the trueth of that Golden Sentence, <hi>Heere wee haue no continuing Citie.</hi> I,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14</note> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5665:3"/>baſeſt in all reſpectes my LORD and MASTER hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about the building of His Tabernacle, longing now to bee diſſolved, and to bee with Him whome my Soule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth; haue out of that affection which I carrie to all ſuch as call upon His Name, beene bolde (over-comming at length manie difficulties) to offer theſe few Lines unto the view of others; that if it were poſſible ſome one ſimple Soule or two, might bee mooved by them (GOD beeing happilie with them) to looſe their affections from thinges heere beneath, and to ſet them upon thoſe thinges which are aboue. I haue dedicated them unto your Honour, whome GOD hath ſo happily weaned from the deceitfull Milke of all things earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and ſo Graciouſlie married unto His bleſſed Sonne: that nowe your Honour can wiſelie account of nothing, but in ſo farre as it leadeth you unto Him who out of loue gaue Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for you. Accept theſe Lines, Madame, as a Teſtimonie of that Loue and Reverence which I muſt carrie to that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Grace of GOD beſtowed happilie upon you: for the continuance and encreaſe whereof, I ſhall never ceaſe to draw up my ſimple Prayers, unto that GOD who is readie to heare all ſuch as call upon Him in trueth, &amp; is able to keepe your Honour unto His everlaſting Kingdome.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladiships, in our Bleſſed Saviour, the</hi> LORD IESVS, <hi>D. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:5665:3"/>
            <head>AN HEAVENLY <hi>CHARJOT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> My Soule! waſt thou not ſent downe heere in time, by that bleſſed wiſe Creator, to ſeeke after that aeternitie which is aboue? O my Soule! Couldeſt thou learne to know with what loue thy GOD loved thee; in what accompt thy GOD hath thee, buſilie wouldeſt thou, while this ever-ſlyding time remayneth, ſeeke after that ever-abyding aeternitie. Oh, ô my Soule! When ſhall I beginne grauely to conſider that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable order kept by my GOD, in bringing foorth that great Worke of Creation, praeſented unto mine eyes by that firſt Chapter of holie Scripture? Wouldeſt thou, O my Soule, leaſurelie payne thy ſelfe a little, to meditate aright upon that order: O! with what a loue wouldeſt thou loue thy GOD! O, in what accompt wouldeſt thou haue thy GOD! And ſo, O, with how ſwift feete wouldeſt thou endevour to run, through fleeting ſinfull tyme, towardes that ever-continuing aeternitie, in the which dwelleth Righteouſneſſe! Yea, O my Soule, I muſt tell thee, Could that order bee well taken to heart by thee, were I warming my ſelfe in my Parlour, at the refreſhing and dauting fire of greateſt Honoures, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and daintieſt Cheare, even with my deareſt Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5665:4"/>thou wouldeſt bee able eaſilie, by a verie little nod, to draw mee to the doores, making mee, with <hi>Peter,</hi> to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome ſecret place, that there I might weepe bitterlie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot bee mooved to ſeeke Him, who could not bee ſtayed from ſeeking of mee, becauſe I cannot learne to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Him, who could willinglie account of nothing till Hee found mee. The Worke of Creation is begunne the firſt day, The Worke of Creation is proſecuted till the ſixt day, and a number of good Creatures, of diverſe kindes, aboue us, about us, beneath us, in the Heavens, in the Seas, and in the Earth, brought foorth: But can our GOD ceaſe to worke, till Hee haue made Man? And when Hee hath made him, will He goe anie farther? Yea, reſteth He not then? O my Soule! I charge thee before GOD, that thou remember this: I commaund thee, as thou wilt bee aunſwerable unto GOD, that thou forget not this.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> BVt, O my Soule! what would thy GOD tell thee, by this comlie admirable order, kept by His Majeſtie, in bringing foorth that Worke of Creation? Surelie, That Hee made all the other creatures for thee, which Hee made before thee, and that Hee made thee for Himſelfe, whome Hee made after them. And what would thy GOD, O my Soule, teach thee heereby? Surelie, That all His other creatures could not content Him, untill Hee founde Man. And dareſt thou, O my Soule, attempt to thinke, or alleadge, That thou art made for anie other beſide thy GOD? Yea, dareſt thou reſt upon anie of thoſe creatures, were the ſight of them never ſo pleaſant to thine eyes, the ſound of them never ſo meledious to thine eares, the ſavour of them never ſo delicious to thy ſmelling, the taſte of them never ſo ſweete to thy mouth, the touch of them never ſo alluring to thine other members? O my Soule! manie ſervantes haſt thou: for thy Maker hath made all the other creatures for thee: onelie one Maſter haſt thou; even that GOD who made thee for Himſelfe: and therefore ſee that thou uſe all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5665:4"/>theſe creatutes which thine eye ſeeth, thine eare heareth, thy ſmelling ſavoureth, thy taſting taſteth, or anie member of thy bodie toucheth, as pleaſant ſweete Coardes, ſent downe from Heaven, to draw thee upwardes, towardes that GOD, who made them for thee, and thee for Himſelfe: otherwayes, bee aſſured, thou ſhalt bee convicted; not onelie of groſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, but of high treaſon, forgetting the Giver, and abuſing the gift: yea, for thruſting the periſhing gift into the Throne of the ever-living Giver.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> HEarken, hearken, O my Soule! and belieue mee, ſpeaking unto thee from the mouth of thy GOD, who eſteemeth of thee highlie, out of that loue, wherewith Hee hath loved thee freelie. Haddeſt thou, O my Soule, that hearing eare to hearken unto, and that underſtanding heart, to perceiue, that which thy bleſſed Maker would leade thee unto, by that more than Majeſticke, Glorious, Comfortable Oracle, ſounded by His Majeſties Glorious Lippes, while Hee is about to make Man for Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, after that Hee had made the other creatures for man, <hi>Let us make Man in our owne Image.</hi> Belieue mee, O my Soule! Could this Oracle (never, alace, ſufficientlie as yet conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by man) bee rightlie weighed by thee, thou wouldeſt learne to thinke leſſe of the other creatures: (after the which, alace, ſo manie doate ſo miſerablie; yea, by the which alace, there is a verie worlde groſſelie bewitched.) Yea, thou wouldeſt learne to accompt of none, but thy GOD: yea, not to attempt to loue thy ſelfe, but for GODS cauſe, and in ſo farre as thou findeſt thy ſelfe like unto Him. What? O my Soule! Shalt thou bee made to ſee and heare, if thou ſhalt compare the twentie ſixe verſe of the firſt of Geneſis, poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Mans Creation; with the third, ſixt, ninth, fourteenth, twentie, and twentie foure verſes, of that ſame Chapter; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us to the Creation of the other creatures? True it is, O my Soule, that all theſe were created by that ſame GOD, by whome Man was alſo created; yet they and Man are not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5665:5"/>brought foorth after one and the ſame manner: for albeit our GOD being to create the Light, the Firmament, &amp;c. be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſay, Let there be Light, let there be a Firmament, &amp;c. yet it contenteth not His wiſe, mercifull Majeſtie, when He is to make Man, barely to ſay, let there be a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but he muſt ſay, <hi>Let us make Man to our owne Image.</hi> Thus paſſing from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the other creatures, to the making of Man, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeciall adviſe and deliberation, as it were: and yet heere thou muſt not thinke ô my Soule! that thy powerfull GOD, to whom all thinges are eaſie, brought foorth Man with anie greater difficultie than He brought foorth the other creatures; or that Hee doubted anie wayes about the making of Man: but this is done by Him, that hereby His wiſe Majeſtie, one in ſubſtance, three in Perſon, Father, Sonne, and Holie Ghoſt, might recommend to our conſideration, the excellencie, and eminencie of Man, beyond and aboue the other Creatures; daining Himſelfe to take a ſpeciall conſultation onelie about the making of Man, as about His moſt excellent and glorious Worke. Shall theſe three ſacred Perſons, of that incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Deitie, after mature deliberation, as it were, concurre joyntlie and joyefullie for the making of Man; and ſhould not I, O my Soule! ſummonding all thy powers, with all the members of my bodie, after due adviſe, charge them all to concurre, for the loving, for the ſeeking, and for the ſerving of that bleſſed GOD againe? crying aloude, O my minde! O my heart! O my will! O my whole affections! and ſo, ô my loue! ô my hatred! ô my feare! ô my confidence! ô my joy! ô my ſorrow! ô mine anger! ô my patience! concurre to ſeeke Him, concurre to ſerue Him, who concurred to make you: yea, ô mine eyes, mine eares, my lips, mine handes, my feete, and remnant members, ſee you all concurre to withſtand ſinne, the enemie of that GOD who with joye concurred to make you; and to proue your ſelues alwayes to be His duetie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants, who hath proved ſo gracious a Lord unto you.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5665:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> MOurne, Mourne, ô my Soule! when thou remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bereſt what I was from my GOD, being created by Him in Adam, and what I am now from my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; Mother, having fallen with them in Adam: was I not created to the verie Image of His Majeſtie? being ſo righteous and perfect, that in my whole minde, heart, and will, yea, that in all the powers of my ſoule, and members of my bodie, there was ſufficiencie of ſtrength, and power, whereby I was able to know my GOD, to loue my GOD, and my Neighboure, according to that voyce of the Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thine heart, with all thy ſoule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37 39</note> 
               <hi>and with all thy minde.</hi> And, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy Neighbour as thyſelfe.</hi> And that without anie diſorder, rebellion, or corruption; and ſo, without anie darkeneſſe in the minde, frowardneſſe in the will, rebellion in the heart, corruption in anie of the remnant powers of the ſoule, or members of the bodie: and being thus ſpirituallie beautified, was I not beſide this, that great empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour (greater than the Turke, who ſtyleth himſelfe, THE GREAT EMPEROVR) having all the fowles of the Aire, all the fiſhes of the Sea, with all which is here on Earth to be found, bound by the verie appointment of GOD, to ſerve me, yea, moſt readilie willing, (by the force of His Majeſties bleſſing accompanying me) for to ſerue me. But alace, ô my ſoule! as I am now from my parents, having fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len with them in Adam, I am deprived of that Image of my bleſſed GOD, to the which I was made; and ſo voyde of that righteouſneſſe, wherewith I was then cloathed, being ſhapen and foſtered, as Seth the ſon of Adam and Evah, was ſhapen and foſtered: and how was that? O my ſoule! ſurelie in the ſinnefull Image of his ſinnefull parents; ſo that now, my ſoule is not ſimplie wounded through ſinne, but ſtarke dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes: and therefore no wonder that our GOD (who onlie knoweth perfectlie, what harme ſinne (alace) hath procured to us) ſpeake thus of man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>All the imaginations of mans heart are onlie evill continuallie</hi> And leſt anie man ſhould haue proved, or ſhould proue ſo peart, as to apply that ſaying,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5665:6"/>to theſe of that firſt world, overthrowne by the Deludge, it pleaſed our wiſe GOD, O my ſoule! (after that Noah was brought foorth of the Arke, to pleniſh the Earth againe) to ſound over againe his former Iudgement touching Man, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>The imagination of mans heart is evill, even from his youth.</hi> Oh! ô my ſoule! when ſhall wee learne to conſider rightlie, that third Chapter to the Romans, by the which that Spirit of trueth deſcribing man unto us, as he is out of Chriſt, and deſtitute of the grace of GOD, proclaimeth him to be nothing, but a verie maſſe of vilde, and loathſome corruption: yea, is not this our originall corruption, cleared unto us by the holy Scriptures ſo ſenſiblie, that as wee are acquainted with that good, which wee cannot poſſiblie doe becauſe of it, ſo we are informed anent that evill, which we cannot but doe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. 2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Roman.</hi> 7.18 <hi>Roman.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>The naturall man perceiveth not the thinges of the Spirit of GOD: neyther can hee know them; becauſe they are Spirituallie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. Wee are not ſufficient of our ſelues, to thinke anie thing, as of our ſelues. I finde no meaues to performe that which is good. The wiſedome of the fleſh, is enimitie againſt GOD: for it is not ſubject to the Law of GOD: neyther, indeede, can bee.</hi> Yea, is not holie <hi>Paul</hi> couched under the tyrannie of this fearfull originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, (where-with, alace, wee are infected, O my Soule) compelled to make this confeſſion, <hi>I finde another lawe in my members,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>rebelling againſt the law of my minde, and leading mee cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, unto the law of ſinne, which is in my members?</hi> And, after this, burſteth he not foorth, into that languiſhing complaint, <hi>O wretched man that I am! who ſhall deliver mee from this bodie of death?</hi> Beſides this, O my Soule, is not miſerable man thus depryved of all righteouſneſſe? and corrupted throughout, in bodie and ſoule, made a miſerable Beggar, beeing before ſo great a Monarch, that hee hath no title to anie of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of GOD: ſo that beeing out of CHRIST, the verie meate which hee eateth, the verie cloathes which cover his nakedneſſe, the verie aire which hee breatheth into, &amp;c. ſhall procure his condemnation, ſuppoſe hee ſinned not otherwayes againſt his GOD. But which is moſte lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5665:6"/>miſerable, O my Soule! not onelie is man thus depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of good, and corrupted with evill, made a miſerable Beggar; but a monſtrous Slaue: yea, a Slaue, unto a fearfull Slaue: even unto Satan, that evill one; who not onelie lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, but even worketh in the children of diſobedience:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2.</note> figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt man by thoſe his uglieſt champions, Sinne, the Worlde, Death, and the Graue. When ſhall this bee ſeene, and perceived by us, O my Soule? Surelie, could this bee ſeene, Sinne ſhould bee hated by us, with an unfained ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred: Satan ſhould bee reſiſted by us, as our onelie deadlieſt enemie. Wee uſe to ſay, O my Soule, <hi>Burnt Bairne, Fyre dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi> Hath not that fierie Dragon, long agoe, burnt us all, (alace) in our firſt parentes? Feele wee not, even to this day, the fearfull hurt which wee received by that burning? Yea, carrie wee not, about with us, (goe where wee will) the ſcarres, and markes, of that burning? Should wee not then abhorre to looke to that Dragon, to obey anie of his counſels, were they never ſo apparantlie profitable, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant? For albeit his coate appeareth ſomewhat to bee friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, his heart ſhall remaine alwayes the heart of an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable Foe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> SCarre, ſcarre, O my Soule, with ſinne, as thou loveſt thy <hi>GOD,</hi> and thy ſelfe: for hath not thy <hi>GOD,</hi> who loveth thee with a great loue, with a wiſe loue, tolde thee, That whoſoever ſinneth againſt Him, muſt not onelie receiue wages for his ſinnes; but beſides his wages, that boontieth which is due unto Sinne alſo. The wages of Sinne, O my Soule, as thou knoweſt, is Death:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note> even that firſt death, with all thoſe diſeaſes which leade a man unto it: ſeparating the ſoule from the bodie, and the bodie from the ſoule: and that ſecond death, baniſhing ſoule and bodie from the comfortable ſight of Gods ſaving Face, and gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence for ever; and why wilt thou die thus, O my ſoule? The boontieth of ſinne, ô my ſoule! is ſhame;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.</note> procuring ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion to man, that he dare not lift up his head, before <hi>GOD,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5665:7"/>before Angels, before Men, unleſſe in ſoule he bee ſenſeleſſe, both of his <hi>GOD,</hi> and of his ſinne. This ſhame, was that boontieth, wherewith our Iuſt <hi>GOD,</hi> propined our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the firſt ſinners, O my ſoule! for howbeit Adam and Evah being free of ſinne, were naked altogether, in reſpect of materiall, naturall, ſeene cloathes; yet they were not aſhamed, but could ſtand before their <hi>GOD,</hi> and looke one upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, with a good heart, and chearfull countenance; ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious were they, through the beautie of the Image of <hi>GOD,</hi> which then covered them. Alwayes, O my Soule! no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are they infected with Sinne, by diſobeying the Voyce of their <hi>GOD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7.8.</note> but as ſoone they were ſo covered with Shame, that they dare not looke upon <hi>GOD,</hi> and are confounded, while they beholde themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> VVOuldeſt thou bee freed, O my Soule! from that Death, which is the Wages of Sinne? and delivered from that Shame, which is the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of Iniquitie? I beſeech thee, ſhake off that Shame, which (alace) too manie (miſſeled by Satan) in this our Age, are clogged with; albeit it procure daylie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of new death, and greater ſhame, unto them: and with a good heart, &amp; ſmyling countenance, put thou on that Shame, where-with too few (alace) in this our Age are covered; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it bee able (<hi>GOD</hi> beeing mercifull unto us) not onelie to ſlay Death, and ſhake off confounding Shame; but alſo to procure quickening Grace, and ſaving Glorie. Alace, O my Soule! how manie with <hi>Vincentius</hi> the Hereticke, beſide <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> in his fourtie-eight Epiſtle, while they thinke ſhame to amende their Faultes, thinke no ſhame to continue in their Faultes? <hi>Corah,</hi> with his companions, lift up themſelues againſt <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</note> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> A certaine ſpace is graunted unto them, to adviſe themſelues, about this their ſinne. But dare they not face the matter peartlie? beeing as readie to preſent themſelues upon the morrow before the <hi>LORD,</hi> as <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were? What wonder then, that our <hi>GOD,</hi> juſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5665:7"/>in all His Wayes, cover them with Death, and with Shame, to their deſtruction, who would not confeſſe their ſinne, and willinglie acknowledge, That Death and Shame belonged unto them, becauſe of it, to their converſion? Fewe Sinners (alace) O my Soule, in theſe our dayes, with <hi>Moyſes,</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> with <hi>Daniel,</hi> with that Great Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> can acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and confeſſe their ſinnes, crying: yea, crying aloude, That Shame: yea, open Shame, belongeth unto them: and, That Glorie, and Righteouſneſſe, belongeth to their <hi>GOD:</hi> and therefore, what wonder, that amongſt our Sinners, there bee fewe who haue our Bleſſed <hi>GOD,</hi> to looke their eyes, with <hi>Moyſes;</hi> to put away their ſinnes, with <hi>David;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.6. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 1.</note> to heare them, with <hi>Daniel;</hi> to receiue them to mercie, with <hi>Paul?</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce thy ſelfe, heerefore, O my Soule! worthie of death; becauſe of thy ſinnes, that <hi>GOD,</hi> through His <hi>CHRIST,</hi> may receiue thee to Life. Take the Coate of Shame to thee, for thy ſinne, O my Soule! to the ende, that thy <hi>GOD,</hi> for thy Saviours ſake, who for a while was covered with Shame for thee, may cloathe thee with Grace heere, and with Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heere-after, for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> FOrget not, forget not, O my Soule, to giue in a Bill of Complaint, againſt thy ſelfe, unto thy <hi>GOD;</hi> accuſing thy ſelfe, condemning thy ſelfe, before His Majeſtie, for the ſecret ſinnes committed by thee, hid from the Worlde, yet knowne by Him. And with this, forget not to giue in the like Bill, againſt thy ſelfe, before <hi>GOD,</hi> before Angels, yea, before Men, for thy manifeſt and knowne ſinnes, ſeene by that Sunne which ſhineth by day, and not kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret from that Moone which governeth the night. For if thou, O my Soule! deceived by that olde cunning Deceiver, vvho as yet taketh pleaſure to deceiue, ſhalt attempt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe (for anie alluring promiſe can bee made unto thee, for anie harming threatning can bee pronounced againſt thee) to giue in thoſe Billes againſt thy ſelfe; to the ende, that thou happilie judging thy ſelfe, bee not juſtlie condemned with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5665:8"/>the Worlde. I know one, beeing taught of my <hi>GOD,</hi> who will both peartlie and fearcelie giue in his Bill againſt thee, ayming at no leſſe than thy comfortleſſe confuſion, and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe condemnation. Alace, alace, O my Soule! When ſhall the dead ſenſeleſſe ſinners of this Age reade with atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? conſider with meditation? that fearfull Stile, vvhich that good Spirit of <hi>GOD,</hi> our Teacher, giveth to that Evill ſpirit, the Devill, our irreconcilable Adverſarie? Is not that evill ſpirit ſtiled by that Good Spirit, <hi>The Accuſer of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</hi> Where-by thy Teacher,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10.</note> ô my Soule! the Spirit of thy Father, and of thy Saviour, vvould teach thee, That no ſooner doe anie of the Children of our <hi>GOD,</hi> commit eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie, anie groſſe knowne ſinne againſt His Majeſtie; but as ſoone that Evill one praeſenteth craftilie, albeit maliciouſlie, the names, and ſur-names, of thoſe, vvith their ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>GOD,</hi> crying, <hi>O LORD,</hi> Thy Majeſtie madeſt this Man to Thine owne Image, Thy Majeſtie delivered Thy Sonne to death for him, Thy Majeſtie vvaſt readie, by Thy Spirit, to renewe him; and yet, for all this Thy great loue, hath hee not defiled him ſelfe, vvith abominable Idolatries? blooddie Murders? filthie Adulteries, and Fornications? brutiſh Drunkenneſſe? mercileſſe Oppreſſions? &amp;c. Wilt Thou not, ô juſt Iudge of the Worlde, rub Shame upon the face of ſuch a one, vvho hath ſo groſſelie rubbed Shame upon Thy Name, and upon Thy Bleſſed Goſpel, profeſſed by him? Yea, vvilt Thou not, ô juſt Iudge of the World, adjudge ſuch a one to bee mine for ever, vvho hath (after the offer and proofe of ſuch rare loue and kindneſſe) refuſed to bee Thine? O my Soule! vvouldeſt thou not bee loath that ſuch an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation ſhould bee made againſt thee? eſpeciallie by ſuch an Accuſer? Forget not then, forget not then, to accuſe thy ſelfe, before thy <hi>GOD;</hi> to the ende, that His Majeſtie may bee mooved, out of pittie, for thy Savioures ſake, to excuſe thee: yea, to defende thee, even before, and againſt, the Devill, thine Accuſer, and deadlieſt Enemie.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5665:8"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> BLinde Man, ſlipping the firſt Path, in the which hee ſhould ſtay his ſteppes, is made to fall from that high vvay, in the which alone hee ſhould walke heere; and to deboaſh him ſelfe in that by-way, vvhich leadeth him (alace) towardes that Lake, out of the which there is no redemption: becauſe man cannot ſeeke after that true Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Guide, vvho neyther can deceiue, nor bee deceived. While hee looketh for Life, hee findeth in ende nothing but Death: yea, vvhile delighting unhappilie in his praeſent foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſportes, hee promiſeth great commodities, and comforts to himſelfe, confuſion, yea, condemnation, proue in ende to bee his portion. What Noble wiſe man, ô my Soule! having his young Childe to put to Schoole, doeth not, even after deliberation, make choiſe, both of that Maſter, by whom hee would haue him to bee taught, and of that Pedagogue, by whom hee would have him attended? <hi>O</hi> Man! I muſt tell thee, were thy Raiment never ſo courſe, were thy Cheare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſober, yet thou lodgeſt, within thy Clay Bodie, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Soule, which would bee wiſelie committed to ſome good Maſter, to ſome faithfull, and painfull Pedagogue. But where ſhall ſuch a one bee found? Let no man ſeeke after Man, to bee his Pedagogue; ſeeke after Man, to bee his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: but after that Bleſſed <hi>GOD,</hi> vvho onelie made Man, and is able to inſtruct man truelie, to governe man rightlie. And ſo let man, ſeeking after a Maſter, after a Pedagogue, runne to the Face of <hi>GOD,</hi> runne to the Mouth of <hi>GOD;</hi> even unto holie Scripture, by the which Hee ſheweth Him ſelfe to man, by the which Hee ſpeaketh unto man; inquiring there, To what way he ſhall take him ſelfe; in what way he ſhall keepe him ſelfe, while hee ſo journeth heere; to the ende, when that Night of Death ſhall fall downe upon him, hee may ſet his feete upon the Threſholde of the Gate of that Citie; and bee received with joye, to lodge, even for ever, in the inwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Palaces of that Citie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27.</note> within the which no uncleane thing can poſſiblie enter. Oh, my Soule! when ſhall the men of this Worlde prooue as holilie wiſe, about the governing of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5665:9"/>their Soules, (which muſt neceſſarilie, either liue, or die, for evermore) as <hi>Monoah,</hi> the father of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> was circumſpect about the dreſſing of the bodie of that his ſonne, who was onelie to liue for a while with him? Hee was not praeſent with his Wife, vvhen the Angel of God appeared unto her: but can hee not runne to his God, and ſay, <hi>I pray Thee, my Lord, let the man of God, whome Thou ſentest, come againe nowe unto us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>and teach us, what wee ſhall doe unto the Childe, when hee is borne?</hi> Alace, alace, ô my Soule! who runneth thus to God? Who prayeth thus to God? That Hee, by His Spirit, would teach them, by that bleſſed Booke of His Worde, what they ſhall doe to their owne Soules, and to the Soules of thoſe who belong unto them, while they liue heere. Oh, Lord God, vvhen ſhall that true aunſwere, given by Thy Majeſties gracious Mouth, made unto <hi>David,</hi> Thy Scholler, inquiring Thy Majeſtie about this purpoſe, bee hearkened unto by the men of this Age? bee believed by the men of this Age? <hi>By what meanes ſhall a young man redreſſe his way? By taking heede there-unto according to Thy Worde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</note> That which our Maſter ſpake to the vylde <hi>Sadducees,</hi> touching the grounde of their fearefull errour, denying the riſing againe of the dead, may bee moſte truelie applied unto all kinde of ſinners, debording from the vvayes of Pietie, of Righteouſneſſe, or of Sobrietie: Thou art an Idolater, a Blaſphemer, a prophaner of Gods Sabbath, a Traitor, an Oppreſſor, a Murderer, a falſe man, an Adulterer, a Fornicator, a Drunkard; becauſe thou knoweſt not, and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt not the Scripture, to bee that Booke vvhere-by God, thy Maſter, teacheth thee, vvhat is that thou ſhouldeſt eſchew, vvhat is that thou ſhouldeſt imbrace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> IN manie reſpectes, ô my Soule! is the eſtate of man now (alace) couched under Sinne, to bee pittied; but in this reſpect eſpeciallie, That beeing naturallie ſenſible of the mortall Clay Veſſell, hee is naturallie ſenſeleſſe of the immortalt heavenlie Soule. What man, having a maimed, or diſeaſed bodie, hearing vvho can cure him, knowing vvhere
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5665:9"/>he may find that Cure, ſeeketh not incontinent for that man? longeth not, even with wearineſſe, to be with that man? and yet (alace) while man is not onlie wounded, but dead in ſoule, through a greater number of ſinnes lying on it, than there be haires on his head, he cannot only refuſe to heare that Phyſician, to come to that Phyſician, who is onelie able to cure him; but he can finde an heart to hate ſuch, a tongue to revile ſuch, yea, now and then, a verie hand to ſtryke ſuch as adviſe him to heare that Phyſician, to belieue that Phyſician, and to bee content to receiue his Potions, and to uſe that his Salue, which is only able to cure his ſoule. <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> beeing infected with Leproſie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kings,</hi> 5.</note> informed by that baſe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid who ſerved in his houſe, That there was a man in <hi>Iſrael</hi> able to cure him, will not ſtint till he goe thither: ſo deſirous was hee of corporall health. That poore woman, who was long ſubject to a bloodie iſſue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.20.</note> is not affraide to throng through the people, till ſhe come to IESVS, ſo carefull was ſhee to bee made whole. Can blinde <hi>Bartimeus</hi> (knowing that IESVS was comming by,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke,</hi> 10.</note> who was able to cure him) be ſtayed from crying, <hi>O Sonne of David, haue mercie on me?</hi> yea, which thou wouldeſt admire, ô my ſoule! no ſooner hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth he it ſayde to him, <hi>Bee of good comfort, ariſe, Hee calleth thee;</hi> but aſſoone, albeit he was blinde, he threw away his cloathes, and haſtened unto IESVS. Oh, LORD GOD! when ſhall the <hi>Naamans</hi> of this our Age, leprous in ſoule, by reaſon of their monſterous ſinnes, ſeeke after that water of the Spirit, and of the Word, which is onlie able to cleanſe them? when ſhall the men, the women, of this Age, monſterouſlie defiled, from the toppe of the head, to the ſoale of the foote, through that continuall running iſſue of iniquitie, which maketh them not only uncomely, but loathſomelie ſtinking, in the noſthirls of GOD, of Angels, and of men; ſenſible of GOD, runne with faith towards the Hemme of <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Garment, even His bleſſed Worde, that by it this their running ſtinking iſſue may bee happilie dried up? when ſhall the blind men of this world find feete, to runne with courage, and with confidence, towards that bright Sunne of Righteouſneſſe, and light of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5665:10"/>Worlde, IESVS, to the ende, they may ſee, that the things which bee ſeene heere, are temporall, and not to bee reſted upon: and that the thinges which are not ſeene otherwayes, but by Fayth, are aeternall, and onelie to beeloved, and longed for? O my Soule! for thine owne vvarning, and vvake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, remember CHRISTES loving Invitation, <hi>Come unto Mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>all yee that labour, and are heavie ladened, and I will giue you rest to your Soules.</hi> But, with this, forget not CHRISTES juſt Conviction, if thou attempt to deſpiſe His alluring Charge, <hi>O Hieruſalem, Hieruſalem, which killest ihe Prophets, and ſtonest them that come to thee;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>how often would I haue gathered thy children together, as the Henne gathereth her Brood under her winges, and yee would not. Beholde, your houſe is left unto you deſolate. If I had not come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpoken unto them, they ſhould not haue had ſinne: but now haue they no cloake for their ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> OH, LORD GOD! vvhen ſhall the looſe Chriſtians of this laſt Age, beeing enlightened, and quickened in Soule, by Thy Majeſtie, in Mercie, looking on their dead Soules, in the Face of Thy Well-beloved, beginne to accompt of that Heavenlie and wholeſome Poole, of Thy Sacred, and ſaving Worde, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie now running plenteouſlie (through the force of Thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies towardes us) through everie Citie, everie Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, everie Cottage; ſo that all perſons, of all Rankes, (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee Thou, for this Thy great kindneſſe) may freelie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, reſorte unto it, as thoſe olde <hi>Iewes</hi> accompted of the periſhing Poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 5.</note> which vvas not to bee found, but in the Holie Land; neyther in it, but in the Tribe of <hi>Iuda;</hi> neyther there, but at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> I muſt confeſſe, ô my Soule! That that <hi>Iewiſh</hi> dead Poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> in foure thinges reſembled our Chriſtian liuelie Poole, of the bleſſed Worde of <hi>GOD:</hi> And yet I dare affirme before <hi>GOD,</hi> Angels, and Men, That our bleſſed Poole, of the Worde, ſurmounteth that of <hi>Betheſda</hi> ſo farre in one thing, that if men could take it to heart, where one <hi>Iew</hi> eſteemed of that their Poole, and reſorted unto it, hundreths,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5665:10"/>thouſandes, ſhould eſteeme of this ſoft running Poole of <hi>GODS</hi> Worde: not onelie carefullie reſorting unto it; but enduring their verie life heere, joyfullie delighting to dwell beſide it. Firſt, vvhatſoever diſeaſe bodilie a man was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto, this diſeaſe that <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Poole was able to cure: even ſo, this our Poole, of the Worde of <hi>GOD,</hi> is able to cure the Sinner, of vvhatſoever Spirituall Sickneſſe can over-take thy Soule, becauſe of anie ſinne thou canſt fall into. Secondlie, as none could bee cured in bodie, by that <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Poole, but ſuch as ſtepped in, into it, and were wet there-with: ſo, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible is it, that anie ſinner can bee freed from his ſinnes, by the meane of <hi>GODS</hi> Worde, till his ſoule bee dewed by it; and ſo, till hee bee mooved, and perſwaded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to heare, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, and obey it. Thirdlie, as that <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Poole coulde not poſſiblie cure, ſo much as one mans bodie, till the Angel came downe, and troubled the Water of it: ſo, this Poole of the Worde can cure the ſoule of no ſinner,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.7.</note> till that bleſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created Angel, even the Spirit of the Father, and of His dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Sonne, come downe, as it were, to his ſoule; joyning His owne inward Vertue, with His owne outwarde Worde: and that way ſtryking the heart by His owne Finger, as Hee ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the eare by His Trueth. Fourthlie, as amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> no man knewe at what time the Angel woulde come downe, and trouble the Water, for curing of their diſeaſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; vvhich mooved the ſicke perſons, looking, and longing, for health, reſorting to that Poole, conſtantlie to lye ſtill at it; not departing after manie dayes, vveekes, monethes, yea, yeares, as is manifeſt by the practiſe of that man who lay there thirtie eight yeares. So amongſt us Chriſtians, there is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preacher nor Hearer, King nor Subject, Man nor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, olde nor young, can poſſiblie knowe, vvhat day, vvhat houre, vvhat minute, that bleſſed Spirit of GOD will joyne His Force and Vertue vvith that His Worde, which is heard, making it effectuall to quicken the dead, to enlighten the blinde, to convert ſuch as haue gone aſtray, to comfort the broken hearted, and to confirme thoſe who ſtand. I vvould heerefore advyſe thee, O my ſoule! if thou bee ſenſible of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5665:11"/>thine owne Spirituall wantes, and if thou long to haue them ſupplied, to reſort thither, where thou mayſt heare this Word, crying unto thy <hi>GOD,</hi> with <hi>David, One thing haue I deſired of the LORD, that I will require: Even that I may dwell in the Houſe of the LORD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>all the dayes of mylife, to beholde the beautie of the LORD, and to viſit His Temple.</hi> Yea, it were good ô my Soule! in this reſpect that thou reſolve with <hi>Anna,</hi> that religious old widow, Never to goe out of <hi>GODS</hi> Temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 36.37.</note> but to ſerue Him there, with Faſtinges, and Prayer, night and day. But, ô my ſoule! lift up thy ſelfe on high, and hearken, even with greedineſſe, I pray thee, to the ende, thou mayeſt heare, and conſider, that one thing; yea, that incomparablie profitable one thing, wherein this Heavenlie Poole of GODS Worde, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with His Spirit, excelleth, yea, ſurmounteth, that viſible <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Poole of <hi>Betheſda.</hi> Could that <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Poole, ô my ſoule! even beeing troubled by the Angell, poſſiblie cure moe at once, or one onlie? onlie one at one time, beeing troubled, could it cure, for no moe at one time were cured by it, beſide that perſon who firſt ſtepped in after the troubling of it, as the Scripture teſtifieth. But as for our Poole of the Worde (bleſſed be that GOD who hath enriched, and honoured thee, O my ſoule, with it) it can cure, and make whole at one time, ſcores, hundreths, thouſands, diſeaſed in ſoule, what ever ſinnes they haue committed. O <hi>Peter!</hi> the healing Streames of this curing Poole, flowe ſo aboundantlie out of the fountaine of thy mouth, that Spirite of Ieſus thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, (who came downe upon thee, in the day of Pentecoſt) joyning His vertue with them, that not one ſoule only, not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only, not 20 only, not an hundreth only, not a thouſand only, but even three thouſand diſeaſed, yea, dead ſoules, are that day added unto the Kirke.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 2.41</note> Coulde this be conſidered, O my ſoule! O, how frequently! O, how buſilie! O, how joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie would men of all ranks, and conditions, reſort to this bleſſed Poole of the Worde of GOD! O, how carefullie, and attentiuely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 10.33</note> would men reſorting unto it, with <hi>Cornelius,</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to it! Yea, ô, how earneſtlie would they in their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, awaiting for the Spirit of GOD, vvith the Apoſtles,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5665:11"/>pray for the Spirit! to the ende, that His Vertue, being joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with that Worde, they reſolue for to heare in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Congregation, they might haue their deade diſeaſed ſoules cured, and quickned thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> WOe is mee, vvoe is mee, O my Soule! that ſo manie baptized in the Name of IESVS, ſhould thinke, and ſpeake, of that good Worde of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, vvhich is the onelie Worde of Life, as that Reprobate <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thought, and ſpake, of that good Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> ſounded by <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> unto the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and to himſelfe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.9.</note> directing his Taske-maſters thus to ſpeake to the people, <hi>Let them not regard vaine wordes.</hi> When vvee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conſider this, O my Soule! vvee all condemne <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh:</hi> but (alace) howe manie bee there amongſt us, who ſaye not onelie in their heart, but with their lippes; yea, by their workes, The vvordes of <hi>GOD,</hi> are vaine wordes? O Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Blaſphemers, Adulterers, and other groſſe Sinners! If anie time yee reſorte to the Houſe of <hi>GOD,</hi> vvhat rounde ye one to another? And when yee goe foorth from His Houſe, what bee your ſpeaches? Let yonder Blaſt goe, yonder wind ſhaketh no Corne. Hearken, for GODS cauſe, O my Soule! Our GOD hath not mens Cornes in ſuch account, neyther counteth Hee ſo baſelie of His Worde, that Hee will daine to ſhake their Cornes with it: For Hee hath a baſer winde, of the which Hee accounteth not ſo much; whereby Hee is able to ſhake all the Cornes in the Worlde. Beſides this, I muſt tell thee, O my ſoule! Albeit that Worde which the men of GOD preach, ſhaketh not mens Cornes, yet it can ſhake Kinges, it can ſhake Queenes, and Subjectes, of all eſtates. That ſame <hi>Pharaob,</hi> who durſt open his blaſphemous mouth againſt GOD, and His Worde, founde this to bee true, by a dolefull experience: For ſhooke not that Worde of GOD him, ſpoken by <hi>Moyſes</hi> unto him, out of his Royall Chariot, when hee was ryding ſecurelie there, in the bottome of the Sea, yea, in the Dungeon of Hell? Shooke not that Worde, ſpoken by <hi>Ieremie,</hi> unto <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5665:12"/>onelie out of his Royall Palace, of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> of <hi>Iudea;</hi> but ſcattered it him not unto <hi>Babel?</hi> ô poore <hi>Iewes!</hi> ſaw ye ever an Edie winde, as wee call it, ſcatter an heape of light Chaffe, towardes the foure corners of the Earth, ſo miſerablie, as that Worde of GOD, ſpoken by IESVS, and His Apoſtles, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Fathers, hath ſcattered you, and your praedeceſſoures, theſe ſixteene hundreth yeares agoe? I know a Blaſt, or two, of this winde of the Worde of GOD, which ſhooke a King ſo, that it chaunged his countenance, it looſed his loynes, and made his knees to ſmyte, one againſt the other, ſitting at his owne Table,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.5.6.</note> at a Banquet Royall, accompanied with his Queene, and Counſellers. I knowe a Blaſt of this Winde, blowne by a man of GOD, ſtanding at a Barre, to bee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which made his Iudge to ſhake, and tremble: for while <hi>Paul</hi> is diſputing of Righteouſneſſe, and of Temperance, and of the Iudgement to come, <hi>Foelix,</hi> the Iudge, trembled, ſo that hee might abyde <hi>Paules</hi> praeſence no longer: ſaying, <hi>Goe thy wayes, for this time; and when I haue a convenient time, I ſhall call for thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.26.</note> VVere the emptie Houſes, and olde Livinges, amongſt us, fearfullie burdened, miſerablie wracked, and daylie chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, from man to man, from ſurname to ſurname, looked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it might bee ſeene, that even the deboaſhedeſt amongſt us, might learne to ſcarre from attempting, to ſtyle that good VVorde of GOD, vanitie, or winde. If thou loue thy ſelfe, heerefore, ô my Soule! abhorre to thinke, and ſpeake, of the VVorde of thy GOD, vvith <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and learne to thinke, and ſpeake, of it, as thy GOD hath directed thee: and ſo thinke, and ſpeake thou of it, as of that Milke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the New-borne Babes of GOD are nouriſhed; as of that Bread,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Luke,</hi> 24.32 <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.29.</note> vvherewith GODS Children are fedde; as of that Wine, vvhereby they are refreſhed, and comforted; as of that Fire, vvherby that Droſſe of the remnant of their ſinnes, is purged from them, and they are purified, as good Golde, to be layde up, in that cleane Treaſurie which is aboue; as of that heavie Hamber, which is able to breake, and bruiſe in pieces, all ſuch as dare attempt to contemne it: yea, in a worde, as of that Meate, vvhereby their hungrie Soules are fedde: and as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5665:12"/>of that Medicine, vvhereby their ſicke, and bruiſed Soules,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.12</note> are bound up, and cured.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XI"/> O LORD GOD! VVhen ſhall Men beginne, to haue the Preaching of the Sacred VVorde (albeit it bee ſounded by Heard-men, by Fiſhers, and ſo by the verie off-ſcouringes of the Earth) in anie kinde of reverence? For what heard by mans eare, in this our dead time, is ſo neglected, is ſo deſpiſed, by mans heart, as Thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Worde, preached, is? Alace, alace, ô LORD GOD, that blinde man ſhould willinglie ſuffer himſelfe to bee decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by that great Deceiver Satan; that hee can even deſpiſe ſpeciallie that, which Thy wiſe Majeſtie hath highlie advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Tell me, Tell me, ô my ſoule! whereby is it, that thy mercifull wiſe GOD, hath appointed that ſaving Grace to bee conveyed to thee on Earth here, which is onlie able to bring thee to that perfect Glorie which is aboue? It is not, ô my ſoule; by the touching of thine hand, or anie other member of thy bodie; nor by the taſte of thy mouth, nor by the ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thy noſthirls, nor by the ſight of thine eyes, that thy GOD will gift thee with that grace on Earth in time, which muſt crowne thee with glorie when time ſhall ceaſe: but it is, by the hearing of thine eare, that thy GOD will doe this. Let others neglect this, let others mocke this: alwayes, ô my Soule! when thou heareſt this, I charge thee, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; Yea, I charge thee, that thou loupe for Ioy within me: For by this, vvould not thy bleſſed powerfull GOD, whoſe wayes paſſe finding out, not onlie overthrow, but alſo mocke, the malice and craft of the devill, to His Majeſties great Glorie, to Satan his ſenſible ſhame, and to thy ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort? ô malicious ſubtill Serpent, thou canſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninglie convey by <hi>Evahs</hi> eares, that fearefull poyſon towardes her foule, which was able to ſlay her, her husband, and their poſteritie: but is not my good GOD both mercifull, and powerfull, able to convey to my Soule, even by mine eare, that wholeſome Salue, whereby that thy poyſon is not onlie made ineffectuall, but whereby I am made to liue for ever?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5665:13"/>Thou ſeeſt, thou ſmelleſt, thou toucheſt, thou taſteſt, yea, thou readeſt (ô man) manie thinges: alwayes, underſtand, it is not by thy ſight, by thy ſmelling, by thy touching, by thy taſting; yea, it is not by thy reading (if thou attempt to deſpiſe hearing, and ſo to contemne the Worde preached) that thou canſt be ſaved. ô! when ſhall that ſhining Golden Chaine of Salvation, preſented to us by <hi>Paul,</hi> firſt be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and then be embraced, and keeped by us? <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call upon the Name of the LORD, ſhall bee ſaved: but how ſhall they call on Him, in whome they haue not believed? and how ſhall they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in Him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.14.15.17.</note> 
               <hi>of whom they haue not beard? and how ſhall they heare without a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach, except they be ſent? then faith is by hearing, and hearing by the Worde of GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XII"/> EVerie man naturallie loveth life, and loving life, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to liue: but alace! ſcarce one of a thouſand, doth know, and conſider, wherefore life ſhould bee loved; and ſo, wherefore man ſhould deſire for to liue. The Ambitious man, with <hi>Haman,</hi> deſireth for to liue, to the ende, his Honour may bee increaſed. The leacherous man, with <hi>Ammon,</hi> deſireth to liue, to the ende hee may ſatisfie his beaſtlie Luſt. The ſeditious man, with <hi>Ahitophell,</hi> deſireth to liue, to the ende, that accompliſhing his crooked plottes, hee may throw downe ſuch as hee hateth, and advaunce thoſe which followe him. The avaritious man, with the Foole in the Goſpel, would liue, to the ende hee may inlarge his Boundes, and augment his Summes. The Bellie-god would liue, that with the rich Glutton hee may pleaſe his taſte, and fatte his vylde Bellie, with the daintieſt Fare. But bee not thoſe men, O my Soule! with their deſires, more than abominable in the Eyes of that holie GOD, who made all men for Himſelfe, and no man for anie thing beſide Himſelfe? Wherefore, O my Soule! if thou, loving thy lyfe, wouldeſt loue it as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the Childe of <hi>GOD</hi> to loue life; and ſo, if deſiring to liue, thou wouldeſt liue for the right ende, I would adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe thee, to learne of that wiſe, graue, Heavenlie-learning Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>David,</hi> That this lyfe is not to bee loved, but for GODS
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5665:13"/>cauſe onelie: and ſo, man ſhould not deſire to liue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.17. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Luke,</hi> 1.74.75. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.12.13.</note> but to the ende hee may keepe GODS Lawe. This was the Ende wherefore man, having loſt himſelfe in <hi>Adam,</hi> was redeemed by IESVS CHRIST: Yea, this is the ende, wherefore dead uncleane man is quickened, renewed, and ſanctified, by the Spirit of the Father, and of His deareſt Sonne.</p>
            <p>A Lace, ô my Soule! as men deſire to liue, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to liue, doe ſinne groſſelie; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIII"/> becauſe they deſire not to liue for the right ende: ſo men deſire alſo to die, but, alace, they ſinne in deſiring to die; becauſe the groundes of their deſire are vylde before <hi>GOD,</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes profitable, but hurtfull to themſelues. Could wee deſire to liue, ſubmitting humblie, and holilie, our crooked willes, to the ſtraight will of <hi>GOD;</hi> to the ende, that with <hi>David</hi> wee might keepe His Law; and with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that wee might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit His Children on Earth heere. Could wee deſire to die, ſubmitting alſo heerein our will, to the good will of <hi>GOD;</hi> to the ende, wee might ceaſe to breake the Lawe of our <hi>GOD;</hi> and ſo to ſinne againſt His Majeſtie: yea, to the ende, that wee might bee with IESVS, who is our onelie advantage, both in lyfe, and in death, holie ſhould this our deſire bee, and happie ſhould wee prooue, having ſuch a deſire wrought in our Soules. Vnderſtand, underſtand, O my ſoule! that this naturall life is no benefit unto man, can bee no benefit for man at all; but onelie in ſo farre, as it goeth before Spirituall, and aeternall life; and ſo, in ſo farre, as it hath Spirituall, and aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life following it: for as that olde Saying ever remaineth true, <hi>Nemo renatus, qui non prius natus:</hi> None hath <hi>GOD,</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them over againe, by His Spirit, to bee a Chriſtian, but ſuch who were borne firſt of fleſh and bloode, to be men and women: So that ſhall ever holde true, which our Maſter ſpake of <hi>Iudas,</hi> It had beene good for that man, who is not borne over againe by the holie Spirit, that hee had never bene borne of a Woman: For Death ſeazing on that man, cannot poſſibly but ſende him to Hell; unleſſe before death man ceaſe for to ſinne. And if through GODS Grace man die to ſinne,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5665:14"/>before hee die before the worlde, hee ſhall ceaſe from his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, and reſt with <hi>GOD</hi> for ever. <hi>Bernhard,</hi> meditating long agoe upon this, and ſubſcrybing to the trueth of it, from a renewed, humble, honeſt heart, drewe up this Prayer unto his <hi>GOD,</hi> I beſeech Thee, O LORD, my Father, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe upon mee, Thine hungrie Childe, three Bread, Even that I may knowe, that I may loue, and, that I may doe Thy will; So ſhall I liue: for in theſe three ſtandeth the whole lyfe of my Soule. And againe. It is commonlie ſayde amongſt men, Hee who feedeth well, liveth well. But heere Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doeth moſt groſſelie (ô my <hi>GOD</hi>) bewray it ſelfe: for none can poſſiblie liue well, but ſuch who liue ordinatelie, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie, and humblie: ordinatelie, ſtudying to procure honeſt thinges, both before <hi>GOD,</hi> and man; that neyther hee ſinne againſt his <hi>GOD,</hi> nor by his ſinfull lyfe offend his Brethren. Sociallie, living ſo, that hee ſtudie, to bee beloved of others, and to loue others. Humblie, that while hee is made thus, through the Grace of his <hi>GOD,</hi> to carrie himſelfe, he be not puffed up with pryde, as (alace) too manie bee: But contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie-wiſe, that with the holie Sainctes of <hi>GOD,</hi> yea, with His moſt bleſſed Angels,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.9.10</note> hee caſt himſelfe alwayes downe, before that Majeſtie, who hath beene ſo mercifull, and beneficiall unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIIII"/> O My Soule! When ſhalt thou beginne to loue that GOD truelie, who hath loved thee dearelie, with that ſincere loue which His Majeſtie will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of, as of that loue which commeth from Him, and ſendeth thee backe unto Him againe? Belieue mee, ô my Soule! albeit there bee ſome, yet there bee not manie, who be beautified, and gifted with this ſorte of loue; for thou muſt know, ô my ſoule! that the heart of man, hath beene, and is, clogged, and cloathed, with a foure-folde loue, which would be conſidered by our Goſpellers, who profeſſe, That they know, and loue that CHRIST who hath dearelie loved them, if they had heartes to perceiue His loue towards them. The firſt ſort of loue is moſt corrupt, in the corrupt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5665:14"/>heart, of corrupt man, whereby man loveth himſelfe, and beſide himſelfe nothing, hunting after nothing while hee liveth, but that which may profite or pleaſe himſelfe, yea, not reguarding, ſuppoſe the whole worlde were overthrown with <hi>Sodome,</hi> after that his eyes were cloſed by death. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend loue is corrupt alſo, in the corrupt heart of corrupt man; whereby man ſeeing, and conſidering, that hee is not of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſufficientlie able, eyther to procure unto himſelfe ſuch thinges as hee accounteth to bee good, or to defende, or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelfe, from ſuch thinges as hee holdeth to bee evill; he is mooved, not onelie to loue himſelfe, but to loue his GOD alſo. And yet, while hee loveth GOD thus, hee loveth not GOD for GODS cauſe, but GOD for his owne cauſe: and ſo, as <hi>Demetrius</hi> loved <hi>Diana,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 19.25.</note> who lived by making Silver Shrines unto her. The thirde ſorte of loue is holie, and rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, in the new ſanctified, and ſoftened heart, of the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Childe of GOD; whereby, he having happilie, through the effectuall working of <hi>CHRISTES</hi> Spirit dwelling in him, taſted the Sweetneſſe of the bountie, and of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of his GOD, beginneth to loue GOD, even for GODS cauſe; &amp; that with a more fervent loue, than he loveth Father, Mother, Wife, Childe, or anie other whoſoever. The fourth ſorte of loue is altogether Spirituall, and Heavenlie, tranſporting, even with exceeding joye, and alacritie, the Soule of man from all thinges heere beneath, towardes the third Heavens; whereby the Childe of GOD is not onelie mooved to loue GOD for GODS cauſe, but to loue himſelfe for GODS cauſe, and all other thinges beſide himſelfe, no otherwayes, but in GOD, and for GOD. This was that loue, O my Soule! where-with <hi>Moyſes</hi> loved his <hi>GOD,</hi> when hee forſooke the Court of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſuffer trouble for <hi>CHRISTES</hi> cauſe. This was that loue, where-with <hi>Paul</hi> loved GOD, vvhen hee ſayde, My life is not deare unto mee, ſo that I may fulfill my courſe vvith joye: I am readie, not to bee bound onelie, but alſo to die at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for the <hi>NAME</hi> of the <hi>LORD IESVS.</hi> And this ſorte of loue, vvhich is begun onelie heere, ſhall bee fullie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5665:15"/>in the Heavens. Oh, LORD GOD! vvhen ſhall I beginne to loue no Honour, but that vvhere-by I may ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Thee? No Pleaſures, but thoſe which may pleaſe Thee? No Wealth, but where-with I may haue my Soule enritched by Thee, and with Thee, for the better ſeeking, and finding, of Thee? Yea, vvhen ſhall I begin onlie to loue to liue, to the ende, that Thy Majeſtie mayeſt liue in mee? and mayeſt bee glorified by mee? Yea, ô LORD GOD, let me ſteppe one Steppe higher: VVhen ſhall I beginne to delight to bee ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to the ende, that Thou mayeſt bee glorified? to delight to bee grieved, and pained, to the ende, that Thou mayeſt bee pleaſed? to delight to bee ſtripped mother-naked, of all the earthlie thinges vvhich I poſſeſſe, or can poſſeſſe; to the ende, that I may poſſeſſe Thee? Yea, vvhen ſhall I long, and deſire to die, to the ende, that I may liue with Thee? And yet, could I doe all this, vvhat ſhould I doe? vvhat could I doe? I could doe nothing, but prooue myndfull, but prooue thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and that not through anie grace in mee, vvhich is from mee: (for, alace, ô my Soule! forgetteſt thou not thy GOD fearfullie? art thou not unkinde to thy GOD groſſelie?) but through thine undeſerved favour onelie. Would not that bleſſed Sonne of GOD, yea, that verie GOD of Glorie, thy Saviour IESVS, (ô my Soule) bee ſhamed, to honour thee? bee pained, to pleaſe thee? bee grieved to grace thee? bee made poore, to make thee rich? Yea, would Hee not die, to quicken thee? And ſo, ô my Soule! vvhen thou haſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thy ſelfe, to whome Shame is due for Sinne: vvhen thou haſt grieved thy ſelfe, to whome Griefe is due for ſinne: vvhen thou haſt depryved thy ſelfe of all thinges, to whome nothing is due, becauſe of ſinne: yea, vvhen thou haſt layde downe thy lyfe, vvhome ſinne muſt bereaue of lyfe, having death for its Wage, vvhat haſt thou done? conſidering that Hee who never ſinned, beeing that GOD of Glorie, unto vvhome all Honour, all Pleaſures, all Wealth, and onelie lyfe did belong, depryved Himſelfe of all theſe thinges, and cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed Himſelfe willinglie with the contrarie evils, and that for thee. Bee myndfull of theſe thinges, ô my Soule! and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5665:15"/>not to beg Grace from thy GOD, to prooue thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them.</p>
            <p>FOoliſh Man, pittying manie, cannot (alace) pittie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: yea, hee cannot ſo much as dreame,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XV"/> that hee is to bee pittied: and yet what creature is to bee pittied, as man (who ſhould prooue GODS beſt creature heere beneath) is to bee pittied? <hi>Oh, LORD GOD!</hi> howe manie men lay downe their lyues daylie; and ſo, are remooved from this Earth, by death, before they know by whom, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were gifted with lyfe, and placed on this Earth? And if man, in this reſpect, bee not to bee pittied, let all ſuch, who be ſenſible of humane miſerie, judge. O my ſoule, if living heere I knowe not of whome I haue my lyfe, for vvhome I haue my lyfe; and ſo, vvho is Hee, unto whome I ſhoulde looke, after whome I ſhoulde ſeeke, ſtudying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſerue, and to pleaſe Him, even in the whole courſe of my life; had it not beene better for thee, ô my Soule! that I had never taſted of lyfe? That man who never was, who never ſhall bee, ſhall never (indeede) taſte of that ſweeteſt Milke, and moſte wholeſome Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which is to bee founde in that Heavenlie <hi>Canaan,</hi> which is aboue: But, with that, hee ſhall never bee tormented with that ever-burning Fire, which cannot bee but found in that deepeſt Gulfe, out of the which there is no redemption. But as for that man, ô my ſoule! who lives, and knoweth not Him, from whom, and for whom, hee hath his life, bee ſure die he, before his minde be enlightened to ſee his GOD, before his heart bee mooved to loue Him, to belieue in Him, and his life bee ſo ſanctified, that in ſome meaſure hee may ſerue and pleaſe Him; not onlie ſhall hee bee depryved, of that immortall Heavenlie Inheritance, but alſo adjudged to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe, and comfortleſſe condemnation. Oh, oh, when ſhall the Inhabitantes of this Earth, hearken to that wiſe adviſe, given by that wiſe Preacher, <hi>Remember now thy Creator, in the dayes of thy youth, while the evill dayes come not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>nor the yeares ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, in the which thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them?</hi> When
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5665:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall they ſuffer that great Concluſion to bee brought to their heartes, which vvould quicken the deadeſt, and waken the moſt ſecure, which the ſame Preacher bringeth to our eares in the ſame place? <hi>Let us heare the ende of all; Feare GOD, and keepe His Commandements: for this is the whole duetie of man: for GOD will bring everie worke uto Iudgement, with everie ſecret thing, whether it be good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>or evill.</hi> Oh, oh, when ſhall Preachers, when ſhall Hearers, out of a ſenſe hereof, learne to cry unto GOD, with <hi>David? Open mine eyes, that I may ſee the wonders of Thy Law. Teach me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſaml.</hi> 119.18.33.34.</note> ô LORD, <hi>the way of thy Statutes, and I will keepe it to the ende. Giue mee understanding, and I will keepe it with my whole heart.</hi> Yea, ô would to GOD, that thou, ô my ſoule, couldeſt in this laſt age, ſee and feele that which <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaw and felt in his time; to the ende, that out of that ſight and ſenſe, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt make the like confeſſion before GOD, which hee made; and ſend up the like Petition to GOD, which hee ſent up unto Him: My Bodie, ô LORD, liveth by my Soule, and my Soule liveth by thee, ô my GOD: Be neare me heerefore, ô GOD, neare in mine heart, neare in mine eares, neare in mine eyes, yea, neare in my whole body, and everie member of it, that they may all ſerue Thee.</p>
            <p>KNeweſt thou, ô my Soule! how bleſſed IESVS hath loved thee,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVI"/> be ſure thou wouldeſt loue Him; and out of that thy loue thou wouldeſt be carefull to keepe His Commandements. <hi>Iaakob</hi> loved <hi>Benjamin</hi> dearely: but, ô! how more dearelie hath IESVS loved thee! <hi>Iaakob</hi> pintched with Famine, is content, for the ſafetie of his owne life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.11.12.13.</note> to twinne with <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and to ſend him downe to <hi>Aegypt:</hi> but bleſſed IESVS, to the ende, that Hee might feede thee, and keepe thee, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! will not onlie ſubject Himſelfe to Hunger,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26.</note> but unto cruell death. <hi>Ionathans</hi> loue towards <hi>David,</hi> exceeded the loue of Women: but IESVS His loue towardes thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! exceedeth not onlie the loue of Women, but the loue of <hi>Ionathan.</hi> Scripture telleth mee, Hiſtorie telleth mee, That Mothers haue ſlaine their owne children,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 28.29.</note> to keepe in their owne lives: but neither acquainteth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5665:16"/>Scripture, nor Hiſtorie mee, with anie Woman, who ever was contented, to cutte and dreſſe her owne fleſh, for the ſafetie of her chylde. Alwayes, Scripture largelie telleth mee, That Thy bleſſed IESVS, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! is that kindlieſt Peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane, who could be content to giue His owne fleſh, not onlie to be ſcourged, to be nailed, to be pearced: but to be crucified, and die on the Tree; to the ende, that thou, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! mighteſt feede upon Him, unto life aeternall. IESVS His loue towards thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! exceedeth alſo the loue of <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; Ionathan</hi> (indeede) loued <hi>David</hi> ſo, that he incurred his fathers wrath for <hi>David;</hi> that he was contented heartfullie that <hi>David</hi> ſhould ſucceede to his father in the Kingdome; yea, <hi>Ionathan</hi> oft times hazarded his verie life for <hi>David:</hi> alwayes thy <hi>Ionathan,</hi> IESVS, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! beeing a King, yea, that King of kinges, by whom, and under whom, all kinges doe reigne, would not onlie become poore, to make thee rich; under-goe that intollerable weight of His Fathers wrath, to the ende, that thou mighteſt attaine unto, and enjoy His everlaſting favoure; but alſo, He would die, to the ende, that thou beeing quickened by Him, mighteſt bee made a king, to liue and reigne in Heaven, with Him for ever. Yea, telleth not Scripture mee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! That IESVS hath loved thee ſo, that He hath married thee, that He hath tochered thee, yea, that Hee hath provided a Dourie for thee. <hi>Abigall</hi> is daſhed, when <hi>David</hi> Ambaſſadours come unto her, ſhewing to her,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.41.</note> That <hi>David</hi> would marrie her. It was a wonder, that <hi>Salomon,</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> married the King of <hi>Aegypts</hi> Daughter: But ſhouldeſt thou not bee much more aſtonied, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! vvhen thou heareſt, That even IESVS, the great Sonne of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that mightie KING of everlaſting Peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4.5.</note> hath married thee, while thou waſt dead in ſinne, lying in thy blood, in the verie open Fielde, having none eye pittying thee? <hi>Hoſea,</hi> ſpeaking of this Marriage, bringeth in thy bleſſed kynde Spouſe, ſpeaking thus unto thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! <hi>I will marrie thee, unto Mee, for ever: yea, I will marrie thee, unto Mee, in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 2.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>in Iudgement, in Mercie, and in Compaſsion.</hi> Men marrie Women for a while; yea, for an uncertaine troubleſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5665:17"/>while. Alwayes, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! IESVS hath married thee for evermore; in ſuch ſorte, that neyther diſtance of place, nor death, nor the graue, can poſſiblie ſever thee from Him, or Him from thee. Yea, vvhich is more, that the nearer death draweth unto thee, and thou approacheſt to thy graue, the more ſtrictlie art thou united with Him, and Hee joyned with thee. Beſide this, IESVS hath ſo loved thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! that Hee hath tochered thee: but vvhere-with, I pray thee? I heare <hi>Saul,</hi> craving from <hi>David</hi> an hundreth fore-Skinnes of the <hi>Philistims,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.25.26.27. <hi>Acts,</hi> 20.28. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19.</note> for his Daughter: and I ſee <hi>David</hi> laying downe two hundreth for her. Alwayes, IESVS hath tochered thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! not with Silver, not with Golde, not with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones: but with Blood. Alwayes, vvith vvhat Blood, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! Not vvith the blood of Rammes, of Lambes, of Goates, or anie man: But with His owne onelie moſte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, moſte honourable, and moſte cleane Blood. Beſide this, yet, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! IESVS hath ſo loved thee, that Hee hath provyded a Dowrie for thee: But what a Dowrie? Beare vvith mee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule, if heere I muſt confeſſe, that I cannot tell thee, becauſe my GOD hath not tolde mee: For vvho, living heere, can poſſiblie acquaint the Childe of GOD, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientlie, and perfectlie, vvith the Valour, and Excellencie, of that Inheritance, which is appointed for thee? Some ſparkes of the Excellencie, and Majeſtie, of it, are praeſented, indeede, unto our conſideration,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 12.32. 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 2.9. 1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 3.2. <hi>Coll.</hi> 3.3.4.</note> by Scripture: but fullie it ſhall not bee knowne, untill wee bee where our deareſt Spouſe, <hi>IESVS,</hi> is. Loue this <hi>IESVS, O</hi> my Soule, ſincerelie: Seeke this IESVS, O my ſoule, buſilie: Serue this IESVS, O my Soule, chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie; and let nothing content thee, untill thou bee where Hee is, who hath ſo loved thee.</p>
            <p>IF thou, O my ſoule, wouldeſt prooue truelie wiſe, to that laſt day,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVII"/> after the which there ſhall bee no day, it were good, that thou wereſt carefull in time, to bee certified of the loue of IESVS, thy Saviour, and Maſter, as of that firſt thing, as of that chiefeſt thing, thou ſhouldeſt bee carefull to bee certified of, before all thinges: ſo that publicklie, before
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5665:17"/>GOD. Angels, and Men; and privatelie, betwixt thy <hi>GOD,</hi> and thine owne heart, thou mayeſt ſay, and ſing, Bleſſed bee that IESVS, who hath loved mee: Bleſſed bee that IESVS, who loveth mee. But heere, O my Soule! there would bee three thinges wiſelie conſidered by thee: Firſt, wherefore ſhould this bee thy firſt and chiefeſt care? Secondlie, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is it, that that loue wherewith IESVS hath loved thee, is intimate unto thee? Thirdlie, how mayeſt thou bee certified, that IESVS loveth thee? Let mee poſſeſſe all the Worlde, ô my ſoule! if IESVS loue mee not, woe to mee. Want what I can, ô my Soule! if IESVS loue mee, well is mee. I want that Honour, that Wealth, that Health, thoſe Pleaſures, which ſometime I enjoyed; yea, I am depryved by death, of a loving Father, of kynde Brethren, of true Friendes, of deare Companions; alwayes, IESVS loveth mee, IESVS is with mee: and therefore, well is mee. And muſt I not bee well, ô my ſoule! having Him, who was the ſole ſolace, and deſire, of that holie man <hi>David,</hi> who was a man according to the heart of GOD? For can hee not, treading all Want under foote, and triumphing, as one poſſeſſing all Wealth, crye out thus? <hi>Whome haue I in the Heavens, but Thee? And I haue deſired none in the Earth with Thee.</hi> But, O my Soule!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> how hapned I to bring in <hi>David</hi> before thee, when I was ſpeaking unto thee touching the happineſſe of that man who poſſeſſed IESVS? Was not IESVS, was not IESVS not onelie with GOD His Father, but the verie daylie delight of His Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.26.27.30. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.</note> when Hee praepared the Heavens, and made the Earth? <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> hath a worthie Speach unto <hi>David,</hi> after hee returned to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> Let <hi>Ziba</hi> take all, ſeeing my lorde, the King, is come home in peace. And wilt thou not gladlie bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to ſay, ô my Soule! O LORD, my GOD, let all that I haue bee taken from mee; ſeeing my Loue, and LORD IESVS, is come to mee; even Hee in vvhom Thou, O LORD, my Father, art vvell pleaſed with me; even Hee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 8.12. <hi>And,</hi> 14.6.</note> O LORD, who is my Life, my Light, and my Salvation? This loue vvherewith IESVS hath loved thee, O my Soule! is intimate to thine eares, is ſprinkled, as it vvere,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5665:18"/>on thy bodie, is put into thine handes, is preſented to thy mouth; Yea, is as it were, eaten, drunken, and digeſted by thee. It is intimate to thine eare, by the ſweet voyce of the Goſpell, preached unto thee: It is ſprinkled, as it were, upon thy bodie, by that Sacrament of Baptiſme, vvhereby thou waſt entered into the Houſe of GOD: It is put into thine hand, preſented to thy mouth, eaten, drunken, and digeſted by thee, as it vvere, by, and in that Sacrament of the LORDS Supper, adminiſtrate in broken Bread, and Wine powred out: Telling thee, ô my ſoule, that bleſſed IESVS, being that cleane, and wholeſome Wheate, was heartfullie conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee ground betwixt the Mil-ſtones of His Fathers wrath; to the ende, that He might become ſweet, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Bread to feede thee. Yea, that bleſſed IESVS being that true vine, full of heavenlie ſappe, and juyce, would bee preſſed in the Wine-preſſe of His Fathers indignation; to the ende, that He might be made a quickening, refreſhing, and comforting Drinke; to quicken thee, O my Soule! beeing deade; to refreſhe thee, ô my Soule! beeing wearied; and, to comfort thee; O my Soule! being caſt downe. Thou mayeſt be perſwaded, O my ſoule! that IESVS lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth thee, if thou loveſt Him: for hee never loved GOD, who was not firſt loved of GOD.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 4.10 <hi>Iohn,</hi> 8.47. <hi>And</hi> 14.15. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 15.4.</note> Now thou ſhalt know, that thou loveſt IESVS, if thou loveſt His Worde, if thou be carefull to keepe His Commandements, and if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in in the ſocietie, of ſuch who loue Him, and walke in His wayes.</p>
            <p>ALbeit Sinne, which is thine onelie Enemie, O my Soule! be a moſt alluring ſweet Potion; yet Sinne is a deceiving,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVIII"/> and deſtroying Traytor: and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it being the Arrow of that evill one, who is not onlie a ſubtill Foxe, but alſo a bloodie Lyon. O! how eaſilie ſuffer vilde men themſelves to be perſwaded, that Sinne may be committed; yea, that Sinne is committed behinde backe; albeit there was never anie ſinne committed but in ſight. It may be, that ſinne be committed behinde the backe of blinde man, who ſeeth nothing, and of ſand-blinde man, who ſeeth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5665:18"/>little: yet is it ever committed in His ſight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 94.8.9.10.</note> who made the eye of man to ſee, and who knoweth his thoughtes a farre off. And ſo in the eyes of that holie One,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.14.</note> whoſe eyes are like a flame of fire; Yea, who is all eye, as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeaketh: Kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thou not, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! that <hi>Abell</hi> was ſlaine behinde backe, and yet in ſight: behinde the backe of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſis,</hi> 4.</note> the father of his fleſh; yet in the ſight of GOD, the father of his ſpirit. <hi>Vriah</hi> was ſlaine by <hi>David,</hi> being farre from <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.</note> behinde the backe of all <hi>Iudah;</hi> yea, and of <hi>Ammon,</hi> by whoſe ſworde hee fell, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ioab</hi> onlie beeing excepted; yet <hi>Vriah</hi> was ſlaine by <hi>David,</hi> in his ſight who filleth the Heavens and the Earth; and from whom none can hide himſelfe in ſecret place:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.24.</note> and this I thinke <hi>David</hi> vvas compelled afterwardes to knowe, notwithſtanding of all his policie. Who in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> coulde poſſiblie thinke, That <hi>Naboth</hi> was cruellie put to death; and ſo,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.17.18.</note> that <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebel</hi> (who ſhould haue prooved his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors) were his fierce Perſecuters, even unto death? ſeeing hee was convicted by a formall Aſſize, having Witneſſes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying, that hee had blaſphemed GOD, and the King. And yet that bleſſed GOD, vvho ſearcheth the heartes, and vvho judgeth, not according to the outward appearance, but righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement, can both accuſe <hi>Ahab,</hi> of Oppreſſion and Murder, and puniſh him for the ſame. Oh! ô my ſoule! When ſhall the blinde men of this dead Age, learne to hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and to belieue, that bleſſed Spirit of Trueth, vvho cannot lie: teaching us clearlie, That no ſinne can bee committed in ſecret. Came never that Sentence (ô my Soule) to thine Eares? <hi>Vnderſtand, yee unwiſe amongst the People: And, yee Fooles, when will yee bee wiſe? Hee that planted the Eare, ſhall Hee not heare? Or Hee that formed the Eye, ſhall Hee not ſee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.8.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Or Hee that chastizeth the Nations, ſhall Hee not correct? Or Hee that teacheth man knowledge, ſhall Hee not know?</hi> Hath that come to thine Eares, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! <hi>Whither ſhall I flee from Thy Spirite? If I aſcende unto Heaven, Thou art there: If I lye downe in Hell, Thou art there: Let mee take th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Winges of the Morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7.8.9.10.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and dwell in the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of the Sea, yet thither ſhall Thine Hand leade mee, and Thy Right Hand holde mee. If I ſay, Yet the Darkneſſe ſhall hyde mee,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5665:19"/>even the Night ſhall bee light about mee: yea, the Darkneſſe bydeth not from Thee: but Night ſhyneth as the Day: the Darkneſſe and Light, are both alyke.</hi> Came ever that unto thine Eares, ô my Soule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Woe unto them that ſeeke deepe to hyde their counſell from the LORD: for their workes are in darkneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 29.15</note> 
               <hi>and they ſay, Who ſeeth us? And, who knoweth us? I haue ſeene thine Adulteries, and thy Lyinges, the filthineſſe of thy Whoredomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier,</hi> 13.27.</note> 
               <hi>upon the Hilles, in the Fieldes, and thine Abominations.</hi> O my Soule! knoweſt thou not Him, who ſaw <hi>Nathanael,</hi> before <hi>Philip</hi> called him, when hee was under the Figge Tree?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1.48.</note> Yea, knoweſt thou not Him, who knewe the verie thought of the heart of <hi>Simeon,</hi> the Phariſee, ſpeaking thus within himſelfe of thy Saviour, <hi>If this Man were a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Hee would ſurelie haue knowne what manner of Woman this is, which toucheth Him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 7.39.40.</note> 
               <hi>for ſhee is a Sinner.</hi> Oh! ô my ſoule! when ſhall that which was ſeene, felt, and confeſſed, by olde <hi>Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard,</hi> who lived in that blinde Age, which was couched un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der groſſe Darkneſſe, bee ſeene, bee felt, and bee confeſſed by us? who liue nowe, hauing that great ſhyning light of the Goſpel, continuallie with her hote pearcing Beames, ſtryking, as it were, our verie Eyes, ſo that wee cannot hyde our ſelues from them, eyther LORDS Day, or Weeke day: yea, eyther by day, or by night. Bringeth hee not in the wicked man, ſpeaking thus to himſelfe, <hi>Parietes inquit ſunt undi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>ue, quis me videt?</hi> I am incloſed on all ſides with walles, vvho ſeeth me? Alwayes, how is that wicked man anſwered by him? <hi>Esto, nemo te videt non tamen nullus; videt te Angelus bonus, videt te angelus malus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernhard.</note> 
               <hi>videt te bonis &amp; malis Angelis major, Deus.</hi> I giue thee (ſayeth <hi>Bernhard</hi>) that no man ſeeth thee, yet dareſt thou ſay, that none ſeeth thee? the good Angell ſeeth thee, the evill angell ſeeth thee alſo: and, vvhich is more, one who is greater than good and evill angels ſeeth thee; to wit, GOD. When that evill angell, the devill, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! ſeeth thee; thy irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliable Adverſarie, and bitter Accuſer, ô my Soule! ſeeth thee. When GODS good Angell ſeeth thee, that witneſſe ſeeth thee, who vvill beare teſtimonie againſt thee; yea, thy loving Brother ſeeth thee, whom by thy ſinne thou grieveſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie. When thy <hi>GOD</hi> ſeeth thee, that judge ſeeth thee,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5665:19"/>who neyther can bee poſſibilie fruſtrate of His purpoſe, nor anyways corrupted when He goeth to judgement. Attempt not heerefore, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! to commit ſinne, upon hope of ſecreſie: for I muſt aſſure thee, from the mouth of thy GOD, that if thou ſhalt ſinne againſt Him, thou ſhalt bee ſeene by Him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIX"/> SInne and Evill, are ſo joyntlie knit together, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! let Satan alleadge vvhat he will, let men miſled by Satan, alleadge what they pleaſe, that vvhoſoever committeth ſinne, doeth evill, albeit neither in the eyes of other men, neither in his owne eyes, yet in the eyes of that good GOD, before whome ſinne was never good, before whom ſinne ſhall never be good: yea, before whom ſinne hath ever beene evill, ſinne ſhall ever remaine evill, commit it who ſo will. I pray thee, heerefore, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! while thou breatheſt heere, forget not to thinke grauelie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that warning and vvakening Sentence, which is delivered by the Spirit, touching <hi>David</hi> his adulterie and murther: <hi>And when the wife of</hi> Vriah <hi>heard that her huſband,</hi> Vriah, <hi>was dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.26.27.</note> 
               <hi>ſhee mourned for her huſband. So when the mourning was past,</hi> David <hi>ſent, and tooke her to his Houſe, and ſhe became his Wife.</hi> Alwayes, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, hearken, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule, unto that which followed. But the thing that <hi>David</hi> had done was evill in the ſight of the LORD. Alwayes, leſt this evill which ever accompanieth ſinne, be miſtaken by thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! thou muſt know, that howbeit Sinne bee evill in the ſight of the LORD; yet the evill of Sinne is not hurtfull to the <hi>LORD,</hi> againſt whom it is committed: but onelie unto that Soule, by the which it is committed. For as mans goodneſſe cannot profite his <hi>GOD;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh,</hi> 35.6.7 8.</note> ſo his ſinne cannot harme His Majeſtie. Oh! ô my Soule! When ſhall the deboaſhed Goſpellers of this our Tyme, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theſe Oracles of GOD to take roote downwarde in their heartes? to the ende, they may bring foorth Fruite upwards in their lyues. <hi>Doe they provoake Mee to wrath,</hi> (ſayeth the Lord) <hi>and not themſelues to the confuſion of their owne faces?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>It ſhall not bee well with the Wicked, neyther ſhall hee prolong his dayes: but hee ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5665:20"/>bee lyke a ſhadow, becauſe hee feareth not before GOD.</hi> As thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy ſelfe then, ô my ſoule! ſtrengthen thy ſelfe againſt all Sinne, if thou wouldeſt not haue mee to repent, (albeit, alace, out of tyme, after death, and judgement) That ever I was borne. For that Evill, which ever accompanieth the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for Sinne, muſt, in deſpight of Devils, and men, at length ceaze upon the Sinner: unleſſe, by ſincere repentance, (GOD beeing mercifull unto him, for His Sonne IESVS His ſake) hee quyte himſelfe, tymouſlie, of Sinne.</p>
            <p>THE Wyſe Gardener judgeth of his Tree, by its Fruite; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XX"/> as the vertuous Husbandman judgeth of his Seede, according to his Harveſt: But, oh! <hi>O</hi> my Soule! When ſhalt thou, learning to bee holilie, and truelie wyſe, beginne to judge of Sinne, thine onelie Enemie, by that fruite, by that harveſt (alace) which it bringeth foorth? Oh, <hi>LORD GOD!</hi> oh, <hi>LORD GOD!</hi> how fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bitter is that fruit, which that rotten poyſoning tree of Sin bringeth foorth! How fearfullie hurtfull is that uncouth har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt which followeth it! I muſt tell thee heere, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! that that Sinne, whereinto I was conceived, and borne, and which (alace) I muſt alwayes keepe within my boſome, while I liue heere, bringeth foorth fruite, bringeth foorth ſheaues; yea, ſuch ſtoukes, ſuch ſtackes, which bee ſo fearfullie bitter, ſo horriblie hurtfull, that if this bitterneſſe, and hurt, coulde bee perceived, even by us, who call our ſelues GODS Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, wee ſhould bee eaſilie mooved, with that choſen Veſſell of GOD, unceſſantlie to crye out, <hi>O miſerable man, that I am! who ſhall deliver mee from this bodie of death?</hi> Knoweſt thou not, ô my Soule!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman.</hi> 7.</note> that thou, and this my bodie, came joyntlie in one minute, joyned together in this Worlde? as two kynde Twinnes, loving other moſte entirelie, embracing other moſt kyndlie. Yea, knoweſt thou not, ô my Soule! that thou, and this my bodie, haue lived, ſince that time of my birth, in this Worlde, ſome yeares together, as husband and wife, moſte ſtrictlie married one to another, even before GOD, and by GOD? and yet that bitter roote of Sinne, which (alace)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5665:20"/>was conceived, was borne, and which hath lived with us, will haue (in deſpight of all wee can deviſe, or doe) thee, O my ſoule! ſeparate from this bodie of mine; and this my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſeparate from thee. But will bitter Sinne ſtay heere, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this bee a ſharpe ſtroake? Not, ô my Soule! For Sinne, even after this ſeparation is made, will haue that bodie, within the which it ſome-time lodged: (for heere I am ſpeaking, ô my Soule! of the verie condition of GODS Sainctes onelie) albeit it bee diſlodged, and put out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, by death, couched under the vildeſt ſtinke, and moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous flewar, that ever came to the noſthrils of man; (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that that bodie was ſometime pleaſant to the eyes of the beholders, and ſavourie to the ſmell of ſuch as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached neare unto it) in ſuch ſorte, that the loving father may not ſuffer that his tender childe, beeing dead, to abide in one houſe with him: that the pittiefull hearted mother can bee contented, that the dead corpſe of her deareſt childe, even within ſome few houres, bee put foorth of her doores. But heere, ô my foule! Wondereſt thou not, that a more vilde ſtinke, that a more loathſome flewar, over-taketh, and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, from the verie dead corpſe of GODS Children, than from the dead Carions, of other creatures, as of Fowles, of Fiſhes, and of Beaſtes? O my Soule! ceaſe to wonder at this, and learne to thinke upon that loathſome ſpring, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from this proceedeth. I muſt tell thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! that the bodie of the holieſt man that ever lived on earth heere, (that Glorious Sacred Bodie of bleſſed IESVS beeing excepted) lodgeth a more vilde gueſt, a more ſtinking gueſt, (onelie loathſome to GOD, and His Angels) than ever the bodie of anie Fowle, Fiſh, or Beaſt, did lodge. I muſt confeſſe, indeede, that the bodies of thoſe creatures doe lodge corruption, yea, much corruption, as may eaſilie bee perceived while they doe liue, and eſpeciallie, when they bee dead. Alwayes, that ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king loathſome gueſt of Sinne, they doe not lodge, which the verie bodies of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iaakob, Peter, Iames, Iohn, Paul,</hi> could not but lodge: And therefore, no wonder, that a more noyſome ſtinke, flow from the verie dead bodies of GODS
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5665:21"/>Saincts, than from the Carions of thoſe reaſonleſſe creatures. But will Sinne ſtay heere, O my ſoule! albeit this be a deepe ſtroake? No, no, for Sinne will haue that dead ſtinking body, in the which it lodged ſometimes, couched under the earth, under the ſeas, and there returne into duſt, out of the which is was taken.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7.</note> But vvill Sinne ſtay heere, albeit this would ſeeme to bee that dead ſtroake, beyond the vvhich none can goe, in the chide of GOD? No, no; for telleth not Hiſtorie us, that out of the dead ſtinking corpſe of men, and women, there ariſeth moſt monſterous, and noyſome beaſtes? Yea, uglie Toades, and cruell Serpents. <hi>Augustine,</hi> in his fourtie eight Sermon to his Brethren the <hi>Heremites,</hi> affirmeth, That Toades are bredde in the braines of the dead corpſe; and, That Serpents are bredde in their Neares. Yea, writeth not <hi>Augustine,</hi> That hee, being at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaw a Toade in the Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panne of one of their Emperours? Dare I here forget the like uncouth ſpectacle, (by GODS ſpeciall providence, I doubt not, for my better reſolution anent the veritie of the thinges alleadged) preſented to mine owne eyes, beeing in the Kirke yarde of LEITH, in the Month of Iune, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſixe hundreth, and fifteene yeares? for beeing there, delightning to attend, for a while, thoſe honeſt men, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, for the time, our Steeple, I behelde, within a graſſie buſh, the heade of ſome dead corpſe, having, in the outmoſt part of it, a little voyde; while I haue a purpoſe, to cauſe the Kirke Officer put this ſkull under the earth, looking on it more narrowlie, I behelde, through the voyde part of it, (to my great aſtoniſhment) a Toade of an hudge bigneſſe: whereupon I called the worke-men, to conſider the ſpectacle vvith mee: and having made a little diſcourſe unto them, upon the Miſeries, Vanitie, Vildneſſe, and Pride, of man, we all beganne to conſider, how vvee might haue the Toade ſeparated from the head; but that wee found altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, till the bone was violentlie broken, ſo little was the voyde part of it, and ſo big was the Toade. Let the reader judge where this Toade was bred, and foſtered: For He who knoweth all thinges, (bleſſed bee His Name) knoweth,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5665:21"/>that I ſaw it lodged, as ſaid is. O my ſoule! what if thoſe thinges could be conſidered by men? and eſpeciallie by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in this our licentious fooliſh Age? would they take ſuch paines, and delight, to fat their claye bodies, with all ſort of pleaſures, and pleaſant thinges, as they doe? Would they, even with the wracke of their eſtates, feede their bellies? dreſſe their heades? cover their backes, ſo daintilie, ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie, which muſt be brought ſo low, and bee made a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to conceiue, a nurſe to foſter, yea, a lodging to keepe ſuch uglie monſters? Yea, if this could be conſidered, O my Soule! O! with what an hatred would the Childe of GOD hate Sinne! O! with what a care would the Child of GOD arme himſelfe, againſt Sinne! ſeeing nothing beſides Sinne, hath brought all theſe evils upon poore miſerable Man.</p>
            <p>IN this laſt, and worſt Age of the Worlde, (alace) O my Soule! all men, almoſt, ſeeke after Sinne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXI"/> defile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with Sinne; yea, alace, delight themſelues in Sinne: and all becauſe few men, alace, ſtudie to acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, truelie, with the nature of Sinne. Men, now-a-dayes, O my Soule! miſcarried by their owne deceiving Luſtes, while they fall into Sinne, looke unto men, yea, unto men onelie; as if Sinne were committed againſt man, yea, againſt man onelie. And out of this falſe ground, blindlinges, alace, layde by them, as they thinke of the man, with whome they haue to doe; ſo they thinke of the ſinne, which they haue committed. If that man bee ſuch a one, who may grieue and annoy them, then they are grieved for their ſinne. Alwayes, not becauſe that Great GOD is abuſed by them: but becauſe a man, who may grieue them, is grieved by them. If that man bee ſuch a man, who cannot grieue them, who dare not attempt to annoy them, by reaſon of their grandour and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit worldlie, and his baſeneſſe, and lacke of moyen with men; O, then, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! they can both digeſt their ſinne ſweetlie, and goe on in their ſinne peartlie, and pleaſantlie: For can thoſe men poſſiblie dreame, that anie beſide man, hath anie intreſt, to quarrell them for their ſinne? Alwayes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5665:22"/>hearken, hearken, O my Soule! would man ſuffer that good Worde of GOD, which is that Worde of Trueth, (which never deceived any man, which never ſhall deceiue any man) to leade him; hee ſhould finde, that everie ſinne committed on earth, beneath heere, (bee the committer of it King or coatter) looketh not lower than the Heaven of Heavens; and ſo he ſhould finde, that ſinne committed beneath heere, is committed againſt none who liveth heere beneath; but onelie againſt that Supreame Majeſtie, who ruling over all thinges, hath His Throne ſet aboue all Thrones, even in the higheſt Heavens. I will confeſſe, ô my ſoule! that a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may offende, and grieue, his King; that a King may injure, and grieue, his Subject; that a Father may hurt and grieue his ſonne; that a ſonne may hurt and grieue his Father; but Scripture beeing well conſidered, will not ſuffer mee to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that a Subject can ſinne againſt his King, or that a King can ſinne againſt his Subject; that a father can ſinne againſt his ſonne, or a ſonne ſinne againſt the Father. Tell mee, tell me, O my ſoule! vvhat calleſt thou ſinne? Sinne, I know, being taught of GOD, is, <hi>The Tranſgreſsion of the Law.</hi> But of whoſe Law,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.4.</note> I pray thee? Not of the Law of anie pettie King; but of the Law of that <hi>KING</hi> of Kinges, who is that onelie Supreame Law-giver, who is able to ſaue, and deſtroy. Knoweſt thou not,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames,</hi> 4.12.</note> ô my Soule! wherefore Theft is Sinne? and when Theft is Sinne? wherefore Murder is Sinne? and when Murder is Sinne? and ſo foorth, of all other Sinnes. Becauſe GOD hath forbidden them; and when GOD for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth them; are they not ſinnes, and not other wayes? Haſt thou not heard, O my Soule! that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpoyled the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> of all their lewels?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 11.2.3. <hi>And</hi> 12.35.36.</note> Yet, I thinke, thou wilt ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accuſe, nor convict them, for their deede: and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was done of them, by the ſpeciall commaundement of His Mouth, who can commaund no wrong. Yea, haſt thou not heard, ô my Soule! that <hi>Ebud</hi> killed <hi>Aeglon?</hi> Yet thou muſt thinke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges,</hi> 3.20.21.22.</note> that hee cannot bee reputed a Murderer for that; it being done, by the ſecret commiſſion of that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame LORD, who hath couched all, living ſo under Law, that Hee himſelfe alone doeth remaine free from all Law: yea,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5665:22"/>farre aboue all Law. <hi>David,</hi> againe, O my Soule! beeing a great King amongſt men heere, hath defiled but the wife of his meane honeſt Subject: yea, <hi>David</hi> hath, by the hand of the <hi>Ammonite,</hi> ſlaine the Husband of this wife, defiled by him. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, ſinneth not <hi>David,</hi> O my ſoule? Yes, yes, hee ſinneth groſſelie; albeit not againſt <hi>Bathſeba,</hi> whoſe chaſtitie was defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; albeit not againſt <hi>Vriah,</hi> whoſe life was taken; yet hee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt that Mightieſt <hi>KING,</hi> who had ſayde, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adulterie: Thou ſhalt doe no Murder.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodus,</hi> 20.</note> The ſight and ſenſe of this Trueth, ô my ſoule! mooved the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened mynde, the renewed and ſanctified heart, of the ſame <hi>David,</hi> to untie his lippes, to proclaime aloude, before GOD, Angels, and Men, that notable Confeſſion, <hi>Against Thee, against Thee, onelie, haue I ſinned, and done evill in Thy ſight.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 51.4.</note> Haſt thou ſinned then, O my Soule! ſo ſecretlie, that no man knoweth thy ſinne? Is that partie, whome thou, by thy knowne and publicke ſinne, haſt offended, ſo baſe, or poore, that eyther hee dare not quarrell thee, for feare, or may not quarrell thee, for want of Moyen? Yet let neyther of theſe, I pray thee, ſecure thee: For Hee is aboue thee, whome thou, by thy ſinne, haſt provoked to wrath againſt thee: whoſe Eyes are upon all the wayes of Man; and whoſe Handes bee ſufficientlie able to puniſh Man. O my Soule! Remember <hi>Naboth,</hi> for thy comfort, in theſe evill dayes. Shall not that <hi>GOD,</hi> who required his blood at the hand of his King,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings,</hi> 11.18.19.</note> make inquiſition for everie ſinne committed againſt Him, by whatſoever ſinner? although Hee ſuffer, even wicked men, for a long time.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXII"/> IF thou loue thy ſelfe, ô my Soule! holilie, and wiſelie, to the benefite of mine eſtate, to the comfort of mine heart, even while a verie worlde of thornie croſſes, and temptations, ſhall pricke mee; and to my full, and finall joye in Heaven: I would heartfullie adviſe thee, neyther to commit ſinne, neyther to communicate with ſinne: and ſo, neyther directlie to doe that evill, which cannot bee called, but thine evill: neyther anie wayes joyne thy ſelfe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5665:23"/>with that evill, which thou wouldeſt account not to be thine, but the evill of another. Thus I would counſell thee, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! not onelie, not to bee an Idolater, but not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with Idolaters: not onelie, not to bee an Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, but not to take parte with an Adulterer. But heere, ô my poore, weake ſoule! for the better guarding, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of thee, on all ſides, againſt the poyſoned killing Arrowes of Satan, thy ſworne Enemie; I would pray thee, grauelie to ponder, and weigh, three thinges: Firſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by doeth a man communicate with the Sinnes of others? Secondlie, wherefore ſhould men bee affrayde, anie wayes to communicate with the Sinnes of others? Thirdlie, what ſhould the honeſt wiſe Childe of GOD (who ſhoulde bee aſhamed to bee a ſlaue to Sinne, alwayes kything himſelfe a ſtrong Souldiour, ſubduing it) in this reſpect reſolue to doe? Scripture teacheth me, ô my Soule! that men communicate with the ſinnes of others, by conſultation, by direction, by approbation, by provocation, by toleration, by confirmation. By conſultation, when they adviſe another how hee may doe that which is evill, albeit themſelues doe it not: thus vilde <hi>Ionadab</hi> communicated with the unnaturall inceſt of <hi>Ammon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.4.5. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.20.21.</note> ſhowing him by what way he might eaſilie lye with his ſiſter <hi>Tamar.</hi> Thus vilde <hi>Ahitophell</hi> communicated with the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous unnaturall inceſt of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> adviſing him, even before the Sunne, to lye with his Fathers concubines. By direction, when men, out of reſpects knowen to themſelues, will keepe as it were, their owne handes from an evill turne; and yet command another for to doe it. Thus bloodie <hi>Saul</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated with the villane <hi>Doeg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.18. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.14.15.</note> in ſlaying the prieſtes of GOD. Yea, alace, even <hi>David</hi> thus communitated with the murther of <hi>Vriah:</hi> for was he not ſlaine by his direction? By approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when a man knowing that an evill turne is done by another, alloweth eyther of the turne, or of the doer. Thus the reſt of <hi>Iaakobs</hi> ſonnes communicated with the bloode of the <hi>Sechemites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.28.29.30.</note> murthered by <hi>Simeon</hi> &amp; <hi>Levi.</hi> By provocation, when one abuſing the place hee is ſet into, or thoſe gifts of mynde, or bodie, he is beautified with, abuſeth others ſo, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5665:23"/>hee provoaketh them to doe that which is evill. Thus <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> communicated with that defection which <hi>Iſrael</hi> made from the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> when hee,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 12.12.13.14.</note> beeing abuſed by young Counſellers, and abuſing that place which GOD had ſet him into, by his auſtere rigerous ſpeaches, provoaked them to juſt wrath. Thus bloodie <hi>Iezebell</hi> communicated with all the evils done by her husband <hi>Ahab:</hi> For ſpeaketh not the ſpirit touching him, and her thus, <hi>But there was none like</hi> Ahab, <hi>who did ſell himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of the LORD;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings,</hi> 21.25.</note> whom <hi>Iezebell,</hi> his wife, provoaked. And in this ſenſe, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are counſelled, by the Spirit, not to provoake their children to wrath. By toleration, when a man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4.</note> having au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to beare downe ſinne, by puniſhing the committers of it, overſeeth them, not drawing that Sword which GOD hath put into His handes againſt them. And thus (alace) even olde <hi>Eli</hi> communicated, with the abominations of his vilde ſonnes; who, by their uncleane liues,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2, 29.30.</note> made the people of GOD to abhorre the <hi>LORDS</hi> Sacrifice. By confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when a man haunteth the ſocietie of wicked men, ſo familiarlie, ſo frequentlie, that there-by hee ſtrengtheneth the wicked man, in his wickedneſſe. Thus the Religious man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth with the Atheiſme of the Atheiſt, by haunting the ſocietie of the Atheiſt. The true worſhipper of GOD, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth with the ſuperſtition of the Papiſt, by haunting kindlie the ſocietie of the Papiſt; even when hee ſeeth hee cannot bee wonne. Yea, thus meeke men, chaſte men, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate men, true men, peaceable men, communicate with Murderers, Adulterers, Fornicators, Drunkardes, falſe men, ſeditious men, by haunting of their companie. This mooved <hi>Paul</hi> to charge us, who bee Chriſtians, Not to eate with ſuch men, not to bee companions of ſuch men. But wherefore,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>O</hi> my Soule! ſhouldeſt thou bee loath anie of theſe wayes to communicate with Sinne? Remember, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! GODS Threatninges; and beſides that, GODS Execution, according to His Threatninges: ſo, ſure I am, thou ſhalt bee eaſilie ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from attempting to communicate aniewiſe with Sinne: unleſſe unhappilie thou reſolue, even with vilde <hi>Lameth,</hi> to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5665:24"/>The Moſte High GOD. Are not GODS Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ô my ſoule! thus counſelled by their Father? <hi>Goe out of Babel, my People, that yee bee not partakers in her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.</note> That lying Murderer, ô my ſoule! perſwaded my Grand-mother <hi>Evah,</hi> That if ſhee woulde communicate with him, in tranſgreſſing of <hi>GODS</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, ſhe ſhould finde a ſhining precious Pearle. But that Spirit of Trueth, who delighteth to haue thee living for evermore, aſſureth thee, That if thou joyne with a man in his ſinnes, thou ſhalt not bee ſevered from him, when hee is plagued for his ſinnes. But will not our <hi>GOD</hi> prooue as good as His Worde? and ſo, execute as Hee threatned? eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie when Hee findeth, that His Threatninges are mocked? That will Hee doe, undoubtedlie, O my ſoule! <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> are ſent downe, as thou knoweſt, to the Pitte quicke, for attempting to riſe up againſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Vpon the morrowe all the multitude of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (alace) communicating with them, in their ſinne, will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelues together againſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> crying loudlie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.41.42.43.44.45.46.</note> and peartlie, <hi>Yee haue killed the People of the</hi> LORD. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes, alwayes, came there not foorth ſuch a fearce vvrath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>LORD,</hi> that before <hi>Aaron</hi> can come to them (albeit he ranne vvith all his force) to make an Attonement for them, there died of that Plague, fourteene thouſande, and ſeaven hundreth? While the Wife of the Levite vvas villanouſlie abuſed, (at <hi>Gibea,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Benjamin</hi>) to the death, the whole Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> (alace) vvill communicate with this Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: For when the other Tribes, their Brethren, beſought them, to deliver unto them the committers of that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to the ende,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges,</hi> 20. <hi>And</hi> 21.</note> that that evill might bee put away from <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> not onelie would they not obey the voyce of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but they gathered themſelues together, to fight againſt them. Alwayes, turned not this, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! at length, to the verie over-throwe of <hi>Benjamin?</hi> Nowe, what muſt thou doe, in this reſpect, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! for thine owne praeſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Hearken, hearken, I pray thee, vvouldeſt thou, vvith that valiant Religious Champion, <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> ſtand by thy GOD
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5665:24"/>with anie man, and fall from thy GOD vvith no man; lifting up thine head, aboue all thinges earthlie, all living on earth, towardes the third Heavens, in the feare of thy GOD, and by the eſpeciall grace of His Spirit, conclude thus with thy ſelfe, I will ſeeke, and I will ſerue my GOD with anieman; but I will ſinne againſt my GOD with no man. Let the King with his Subject, and Subject with his King, ſeeke and ſerue GOD, as <hi>Davids</hi> Subjectes with him, and hee with them, did. But if all the Subjectes of the Land forſake GOD, let the King ſay with <hi>Ioſhua, I, and mine houſe, will ſerue the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 24.15. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.17.</note> If the King will fall away from GOD, let the Subjectes with <hi>Saules</hi> Courteoures, looke to him, and refuſe to followe him. And if hee attempt to command them, to forſake their GOD, let them anſwere couragiouſlie, vvith the Apoſtles, <hi>Whether it bee better to obey GOD or Man, judge yee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.19.</note> Let the Husbande vvith the Wife, and the Wife with the Husbande, ſeeke and ſerue <hi>GOD,</hi> as the <hi>Shunamitiſh</hi> Ladie with her Husbande did.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kinges,</hi> 4.</note> But if the Wife, vvith <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, vvill looke over her ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>Sodome,</hi> let the Husband, vvith <hi>Lot,</hi> keepe his heart, and his eye, ſtraight upon that Mountaine of Glorie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 19.</note> towardes the vvhich the <hi>LORD</hi> hath directed him. If the Husband, with <hi>Nabal,</hi> vvill prooue prophane, and ungrate, let the Wife, with <hi>Abigall,</hi> remaine religious, and thankfull.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.</note> Let the Parent with the Childe, and the Childe with the Parent, ſeeke and ſerue <hi>GOD,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſerved Him joyntlie, and ſweetlie, together. But let the Parent, vvith <hi>Iaakob,</hi> learne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.6.7.8.9.</note> not to ſinne with the Childe: for when <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> fell into vilde murder, vvho were both his ſonnes, can hee not crye, <hi>Simeon and Levi, Brethren in evill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>the inſtrumentes of crueltie are in their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, into their ſecret let not my Soule come: my Glorie, bee thou not joyned with their aſſemblie.</hi> If the Father will fall away from <hi>GOD,</hi> vvith <hi>Saul,</hi> yet let the Sonne ſticke conſtantlie unto Him, vvith <hi>Ionathan.</hi> Yea, if the Mother, which brought thee foorth, fall away from GOD, not onelie ſuffer her not; but, if GOD haue cloathed thee with Authoritie, ſee that thou take order vvith her,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.16.</note> as King <hi>Aza</hi> tooke order vvith his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and her Groue: otherwayes, bee aſſured, that GOD,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5665:25"/>(whom thou ſhouldſt not onlie loue better than thy Mother;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 14.16.</note> but for whoſe cauſe thou ſhouldeſt hate all that belong unto thee) ſhall take order with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXIII"/> OH! O my ſoule! when ſhalt thou finde eye-ſalue, to enlighten thee; to the ende, that thou mayeſt once ſee ſinne, in the own vilde colour of it? When ſhall that Dew come downe from Heaven, which may happilie ſoften thine heart, and make it ſo delicatelie tender, that thou mayeſt once feele, ſinne in the owne heavie weight of it? and ſo be made, now at length, to know it in the owne horrible nature, with all it drawes after it, with all it hath joyned with it; and all to the ende, that I, before I bee made to lay downe this earthlie tabernacle, may bee mooved to ſcarre with it; yea, to hate it; and vvith the verie hazard, and loſſe of all I haue, to arme my ſelfe againſt it. Stoppe thine eares, ô my Soule! againſt Satan, and cloſe thine eyes upon him alſo, when he ſpeaketh to thee touching ſinne, when he bringeth thee before ſinne, or ſinne before thee: for belieue mee, hee will tone it ſo, hee will fairde it ſo, that he will make thee take it for ſome ſweet, pleaſant, wholeſome, Apple, while it is that onlie bitter and deſtroying poyſon, which ſlayeth bodie, and ſoule. Open thine eares, O my Soule! to heare thy GOD: enlarge thine heart, O my Soule! to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue thy GOD, when Hee ſpeaketh unto thee touching ſinne: for Hee will tell thee, that ſinne is an uglie defiling thing; that ſinne is a monſtruous uglie defiling thing; yea, that ſinne is a cruell monſtruous defiling thing. Sinne is an uglie defiling thing, making the ſinner foule; yea, even foule in His eyes, before whom alone he hath ſpeciall neede to bee cleane; and ſo, in the eyes of GOD his Maker, and Iudge. Sinne is a monſtrous uglie defiling thing; for none can poſſibilie waſh away that filth which it draweth upon man, beſide that cleane One, IESVS CHRIST, by His owne Handes. Sinne is a cruell monſtruous uglie thing; for even this cleane One, IESVS, cannot poſſibilie waſh away that filth it draweth on by His owne handes, but in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5665:25"/>Laver of His owne precious Bloode onlie. Thou thinkeſt, ô my ſoule! that thou meeteſt with a wonder, vvhen thou heareſt that <hi>Naaman,</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> was cleanſed of his Leproſie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 5.14</note> by waſhing himſelfe ſeaven times in the River <hi>Iordane.</hi> Thou thinkeſt much of that Poole, which beeing troubled by the Angell, was able to cure that man who firſt ſteepped in into it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 5.4.</note> of whatſoever diſeaſe hee had. Yea, thou meeteſt, as thou muſt confeſſe, with an uncouth wonder, when thou ſeeſt thy Maſter vvith His owne Handes, powring water in a Baſon, and waſhing His Diſciples Feete: but, O!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 13.45</note> with what a wonder mayeſt thou meete, ô my ſoule! beſide <hi>Matthew,</hi> in his twentie ſeaven; <hi>Marke,</hi> in his fourteenth; <hi>Luke,</hi> in his twentie two; <hi>Iohn,</hi> in his nynteenth? for there thou mayſt ſee bleſſed IESVS, not ryſing from anie Table, but fixed to a Tree: not powring foorth water, to vvaſh the feete of anie; but yeelding foorth, out of unſpeakeable loue; and with incomparable contentment, His verie heart blood, for the waſhing of the ſoules of all ſuch as can, by a true liuelie faith keepe this His Bloode, keepe this His Bloode. The Papiſt mixeth this bloode, as not ſufficient for him: the Papiſt mocketh this blood, as not onlie requiſite for him: yea, which is more, the Papiſt avowedlie controlleth this which wee ſpeake (being ſo taught of GOD) touching this blood, as not alwayes requiſite for him: and which I muſt neceſſarilie deplore, and lament, ô my Soule! a verie world of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes, in this our time, abuſe this Blood of bleſſed IESVS, onlie able to waſh ſinners, as if it were not ſo precious, ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, as holie Scripture affirmeth it for to be. The blinde Papiſt mixeth this Blood of IESVS, (as not ſufficient to waſh away his ſinne) with the Milke of His Mother <hi>Marie:</hi> But ſpake <hi>Iſai</hi> ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.5.</note> when he deponed that onlie IESVS was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, and that wee are no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes healed, but by His ſtripes onelie? Spake <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1.</note> when hee ſaw a great fountaine opened, for the Houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and to the inhabitantes of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for ſinne, and for uncleanneſſe? Can hee who was ſent before bleſſed IESVS (to ſhew what a one IESVS was) ſee this, which the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5665:26"/>blinde Papiſt ſeeth? No, no, ô my Soule! For is not this his Teſtimonie touching Him?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>Beholde, the Lambe of GOD, which taketh away the Sinnes of the Worlde,</hi> Yea, can that man, vvho laye nearer our Bleſſed Saviour than ever Sainct <hi>Francis,</hi> or anie Papiſt, did, perceiue this? Not forſoothe: For ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hee not thus, <hi>The Bloode of IESVS CHRIST clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us from all Sinne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1.7,</note> The blinde Papiſt, ô my Soule! moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this alſo: as if <hi>CHRISTES</hi> Bloode were not fit onelie to waſh away Sinne. And therefore, hee dare maintaine, That thoſe villanous Poenitentiaries (vvho are accuſtomed, vvith the Prieſtes of <hi>Baal,</hi> cruellie to launce themſelues, to the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their blood) doe not lyinglie thinke, That thereby they deſerue Remiſſion of Sinnes, at the handes of that Great Majeſtie. O, vilde Papiſt! Bee aſhamed heere. Is not thy blood ſuch a blood, as thou thy ſelfe art? Vilde art thou; for thou art a ſinner: and I muſt thinke, that thy bloode is as vilde: for is it not the blood of a ſinner? And can the vilde blood, of a vilde ſinner, poſſiblie pacifie the vvrath of that holie GOD, before whom the Heavens are not cleane? and vvho found no ſteadfaſtneſſe in His Sainctes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob,</hi> 15.15.</note> O, vilde Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt! Was it ever lawfull, to ſacrifice a Man to GOD? O vvilfull, malicious, ignorant Papiſt! Could the verie blood of IESVS haue beene a ſufficient Sacrifice for Sinne, had it not beene the blood of Him, vvho was not Man onelie, but God and Man alſo? And therefore, heareſt thou not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit affirming,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts,</hi> 20.29.</note> That even <hi>GOD by His owne Blood hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Church unto Himſelfe?</hi> This mooved that <hi>Peter</hi> (ſhamed bee the Pope, <hi>Peter</hi> his alleadged, but <hi>Iudas</hi> his true ſucceſſor) to depone,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19.</note> that we are not redeemed by anie blood, beſide the precious blood of. <hi>CHRIST,</hi> that Lambe of GOD, undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and without ſpotte. O Heavens! vvill yee not partie your holie Maker heere, againſt the helliſh Papiſtes? Much blood ſaw that Sunne, which enlighteneth this Earth, ſhedde betwixt that day, in the which <hi>Kain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abel,</hi> and that day, in the which that bloode of IESVS vvas ſhedde on the Croſſe; not preaſſing to hyde his Face. But can hee beholde the Blood of his maker, vvith anie kynde of countenance,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5665:26"/>vvhen it was ſhedde? No, no: for hee covereth his Face,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.45</note> from the third houre, to the ninth. But no wonder: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that day, hee never ſawe <hi>Sanguinem purum, &amp; purificantem,</hi> cleane, and cleanſing Blood, ſhedde. O, harde Earth! vvilt thou not heere partie thy maker alſo, againſt the indured Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes? Much blood drankeſt thou in, betwixt that day that <hi>Kain</hi> ſlew <hi>Abell,</hi> and that day that IESVS His bloode was ſhedde, abyding in the meane time firme and ſtable. But canſt thou, O harde Earth! abyde ſtable, vvhen this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bloode of IESVS falleth upon thee? No, no:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.51.52.</note> for the verie Graues open their mouthes, vvhen that Bloode be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to dew thee; ſo that a great number, vvho were dead, aroſe, and went into the holie Citie. Yea, the verie hardeſt Stones can cleaue themſelues aſunder, vvhen this Bloode is ſhedde: albeit the Flintie heart of the Papiſt, harder than the Stone, cannot bee mooved to thinke honourablie of this Bloode. Alwayes, no wonder is it, O my Soule! that the harde Earth, vvith the hardeſt Stones, vvere ſo mooved: for till that day, ſhee never dranke in anie cleane, anie cleanſing blood. The Papiſt alſo, ô my ſoule! controlleth this, as a manifeſt untrueth: For hee would holde us in hande, That Sinnes may bee waſhen away, vvhere no blood is ſhedde: for is hee affrayde to avow, That his reall, externall, unbloodie ſacrifice of the Maſſe, (as hee, lyinglie, and ſhameleſlie, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by that olde ſhameleſſe Lyar, Satan, and that for his foule particular, ſpeaketh) is a ſacrifice propitiatorie, for the ſinnes of the living on earth heere, and of the dead, in his impure foule Purgatorie? O <hi>Paul!</hi> vvilt thou (ledde by the good Spirite of Trueth) ſubſribe with the Papiſt, in this pointe? No, no, <hi>Paul</hi> aunſwereth, I will never, eyther ſubſcribe neare hand, nor hearken afarre off, unto that abominable Lie: For as CHRIST IESVS none otherwayes purchaſed a Kirke unto Himſelfe, than by Blood; ſo without Blood there is no Remiſſion, ſayeth <hi>Paul.</hi> Our ſenſuall Proteſtantes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.22.</note> (alace) O my ſoule! turning the Saving Grace of GOD, into damnable Wantonneſſe, in this foule Age, abuſe feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie this onelie honourable, and meritorious Bloode of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5665:27"/>IESVS: For he holds not the ſheeding of it for ſinne, to be a ſufficient ſcarre, to affray him from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting of ſinne; yea, from wallowing in uncouth ſinnes, even with delight; as if hee were ſome filthie Swine, made with his Face down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes; and not a Man, vvhome GOD hath honoured vvith His owne Image. Tell mee, tell mee, O my Soule! if any man would, eyther of purpoſe, or with pleaſure, defile his outward Garment, with anie kynde of Filth, if hee could bee perſwaded, that nothing coulde cleanſe that his Garment againe, but a Veſſell full of his owne beſt blood? Now, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not the Scripture thee, O my Soule! That thou, beeing defiled with Sinne, canſt not poſſiblie bee cleanſed from it, but by the Blood of IESVS onelie? Shalt thou then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt at anie time, to commit ſinne of purpoſe? and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſinne with pleaſure? And if thou dareſt doe ſo, canſt thou thinke thy ſelfe to bee one, vvho eyther eſteemeth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourablie of that honourable Blood of IESVS, ſhedde to cleanſe thee; or reverentlie, and honourablie, of that bleſſed GOD, vvho ſhedde His Blood for thee?</p>
            <p>SInne is a filthie thing, Sinne is a moſt cruell filthie thing,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXIIII"/> O my Soule! as thou mayeſt eaſilie perceiue: and let this humble thee. Alwayes honourable, and precious, is that Blood of bleſſed IESVS: Forcible, and ſtrong, beyond meaſure, is that Blood of bleſſed IESVS: and let this comfort thee. IESVS His Blood is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and precious; for it can doe away the filth of Sinne; making a man even cleane, in His eyes, before whom the well informed Childe of GOD, ſtryveth ſpeciallie to bee cleane. Forcible, and ſtrong, is the Blood of IESVS; for it can waſh a man, not from one ſinne, but from everie ſinne; yea, from all ſinnes, were they never ſo monſtrous, ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous. Haſt thou not, ô my ſoule! conſidered, that firſt Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> for thine information? Yea, for thy ſpeciall conſolation anent this point? ô bleſſed IESVS, my ſole ſaviour! of whom art Thou come according to the fleſh? and ſo what fathers, what mothers, will Thy Majeſtie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5665:27"/>(as man) haue? is Thy Majeſtie, O my Saviour, onlie come of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and not of <hi>Pharez</hi> alſo, whom <hi>Iudah</hi> begot on <hi>Tamar</hi> his Daughter in Law? Will Thy Majeſtie, O my Saviour, haue <hi>Sarah</hi> onlie (the wife of <hi>Abraham</hi>) for Thy Mother, and not <hi>Rahab</hi> the Harlot, and <hi>Ruth</hi> the <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> alſo? But wherefore, O my ſoule! would bleſſed <hi>IESVS,</hi> haue ſuch Fathers, haue ſuch Mothers, according to the fleſh? Surelie, ſurelie, to teſtifie before GOD, Angels, and Men, that He came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke,</hi> 2.1</note> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, were their ſinnes never ſo manie, never ſo mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, providing that they, by a liuelie faith, coulde keepe that blood which He hath ſhedde to waſh them; and by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere repentance, accompaning this their faith, teſtifie to the world, that they haue learned, being taught by the Spirit, to accompt honourablie, of this His blood ſhedde for them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXV"/> O My Soule! I will tell thee, to thy comfort, were thy ſinnes never ſo manie, were thy ſinnes never ſo monſtrous, that precious blood of bleſſed <hi>IESVS,</hi> who hath loved thee, is ſufficientlie able to waſh thee from them all. Alwayes, I muſt tell thee, for thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and reformation, That wiſe <hi>IESVS</hi> vvill not vvaſh thee in His blood, from thy manie ſinnes by paſt, from thine uglie ſinnes praeſent, to the ende, that thou mayeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes defile thy ſelfe with ſinne, or continue in the trade of thy praeſent ſinnes: but to the ende,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5.6.</note> that thou being waſhen by Him, mayeſt prooue a Spirituall King; ſubduing Sinne: and a Spirituall Prieſt; offering up thy ſelfe, in bodie &amp; ſoule, in a living, and an holie Sacrifice, unto <hi>GOD.</hi> Tell me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.2</note> tell mee, O <hi>Zachariah!</hi> the Father of <hi>Iohn the Baptist,</hi> Wherefore came CHRIST into this Worlde, bringing cleane, and cleanſing blood with Him? Was it not, That we, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of the handes of our Enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 1.74.75.</note> ſhould ſerue Him vvithout feare? O <hi>Paul!</hi> tell me, wherfore died my <hi>LORD,</hi> and <hi>LYFE, IESVS CHRIST,</hi> for mee? Was it not, That I, hence-foorth, ſhould not attempt to liue to my ſelfe, but unto Him, vvho died for mee, and roſe againe? Yea,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</note> tell
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5665:28"/>mee, O <hi>Paul!</hi> Wherefore hath our Glorious GOD appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that His bleſſed Goſpel to bee preached? vvhich I may juſtlie call, That buntch of Hyſſope, by the which our ſoules are ſprinkled, vvith that cleanſing bloode of that cleane Lambe, vvho maketh that deſtroying Angel to paſſe by us, vvhile others die. Was is not, O my ſoule! that wee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying all ungodlineſſe, and worldlie luſtes, ſhould liue holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and righteouſlie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12</note> and ſoberlie, in this praeſent Worlde?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXVI"/> HAth that Great <hi>GOD,</hi> and bleſſed Saviour of the Worlde, <hi>IESVS,</hi> loved thee, O my Soule? And loving thee, vvaſhen thee from thy ſinnes, in His blood? Yea, renewed thee ſo by His Spirite, that thou dareſt not attempt to liue to thy ſelfe, ſeeking ſuch things as may profite thee, may pleaſure thee: but unto Him, vvho died for thee: ſtudying alwayes, to doe thoſe thinges vvhich may pleaſe Him, and conquiſh Glorie unto Him. Bee ſure, bee ſure, O my Soule! that this bleſſed One, thy great Saviour, enjoying all Priviledges, hath no Priviledge, in a manner, vvhereof Hee will not gladlie make thee Partner. And muſt not this comfort thee, againſt all temptations, and croſſes, if thou canſt loue Him, and cleaue unto Him? And ſhall not this confound thee, if knowing this to bee true; as thou muſt know it to bee moſt true: if thou dareſt attempt to forget Him, and to bee unthankfull unto Him? <hi>IESVS</hi> hath one GOD, O my Soule! and Hee will haue His GOD to bee thy GOD.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 20.17.</note> 
               <hi>IESVS</hi> hath a Father; and Hee will haue His Father, to bee thy Father. <hi>IESVS</hi> is not onelie cloathed vvith an humane nature, but alſo with a Divine nature; and Hee will haue thee to bee a Partner of the Divine nature alſo.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>IESVS</hi> is the <hi>LORD</hi> His <hi>CHRIST;</hi> and ſo, that holy One, vvhome His Father hath annoynted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7.</note> vvith the Oyle of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aboue His fellowes, to bee the Great King, and Prieſt of the Kirke: and Hee will haue thee made a King, and a Prieſt, unto GOD, His Father alſo. <hi>IESVS</hi> is the Heyre of that Inheritance immortall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6.</note> &amp; undefiled, &amp; which fadeth not away: and Hee will haue thee to bee an Heyre of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5665:28"/>annexed with Him. Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> this <hi>IESVS</hi> is entered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie into that Heaven of Heavens, even in my nature; ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there, at the Right Hand of that Great Majeſtie: and He vvill haue thee, O my Soule! to be there,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.24.</note> even with this my bodie alſo: Yea, till I be there, in bodie, &amp; in ſoule, &amp; the whole Elect of GODS Members with me, that holy One, that bleſſed One, <hi>IESVS,</hi> vvho is Loue it ſelfe, (for otherwayes Hee had never died for mee) will account Himſelfe to bee imperfect; yea, to bee maymed, as it were: ſuch is the force of that loue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.</note> wherewith Hee loved us; and ſo rarelie ineſtimable are thoſe Heavenlie Priviledges: unto the full fruition, and everlaſting poſſeſſion whereof, Hee muſt neceſſarilie haue us advanced.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXVII"/> BLeſſed, bleſſed, O my ſoule! beyonde meaſure, be all thoſe, whoſe Father Almightie GOD, in His deareſt Sonne, <hi>IESVS,</hi> hath become: And therefore, I cannot wonder, that that Diſciple whome <hi>IESVS</hi> loved, ſpeaking heereof, was mooved, with a ſhrill voyce, thus to crye foorth; reſembling ſome Meſſenger, ſounding from a Market Croſſe, ſome ſpeciall Proclamation: <hi>Beholde what loue the Father hath ſhewed on us, that wee ſhould bee called,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Sonnes of GOD.</hi> Manie Sonnes, indeede, hath His Majeſtie: yea, our GOD (bleſſed for evermore bee that His only beloved Sonne, <hi>IESVS,</hi> who at a great rate hath conquiſhed theſe Sonnes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him) hath a verie worlde of Sonnes. Alwayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.9.</note> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture telleth mee, O my Soule! That GOD, our Father, will make all theſe His Sonnes, Kinges;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6.</note> and everie one of them a King: not to reigne for a while, honoured with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Crowne: But to reigne for evermore, in that Kingdome,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 3.4.5.</note> which is immortall, and undefiled, and which fadeth not away. What King earthlie, ô my Soule! having manie Sonnes, is able to make all his Sonnes Kinges? And yet foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man dreameth thoſe to bee happie, who bee the Sonnes of Kinges; yea, of great men: howbeit none can bee poſſibly truelie happie, but ſuch, who being borne over againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> 3.3.</note> by the Spirit, and by the Worde of GOD, bee made the Sonnes of The Moſt High: and ſo Kings, at length, to reigne in deſpight
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5665:29"/>of all Tyrantes, and tyrannie, for ever. I ſhall not offende, heerefore, ô my Soule! albeit my Coate now bee courſe, my Bread bee browne, my Drinke ſmall, my Crowne ſharpe, and pricking, having terroures within, and troubles without. Knoweſt thou not, ô my ſoule! howe thy <hi>LORD,</hi> and <hi>SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOVR,</hi> comming to this Earth, by His death, to draw thee to Heaven, was cloathed, was entertayned, was crowned here: and yet, bleſſed bee His Name, in deſpight of all helliſh, and earthlie Powers, is Hee not crowned nowe in that higheſt Heavens, with that Crowne of incomparable Majeſtie, and everlaſting Glorie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18</note> having all power in Heaven, and on Earth, given unto Him? Yea, poſſeſſing a Name, aboue all names which are named in this Worlde;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.9.10.</note> and unto the which everie Knee muſt bowe. O believing Trades man, Craftes man, Coatter, Beggar! Canſt thou lift up thine Eyes afore-hande, to ſee? Canſt thou bow thine heart afore-hande, to taſte, the unſpeakeable Ioyes which thy Soule ſhall poſſeſſe, that incorruptible Glorie which ſhall compaſſe thy verie clay Veſſell, when thou, beeing glorified throughlie, the Lambe, with the Lambe, ſhall goe in, and out, before the Lambe, in that newe <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> which is aboue; having on thine head that Crowne of endleſſe Glorie, cloathed with a long white Robe, having Palmes in thine hand, and crying joyfullie, with a loude voyce, <hi>Salvation commeth of our GOD, that ſitteth on the Throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revelat.</hi> 7.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>and of the Lambe.</hi> Let it bee thy Meate then, thy Drinke then, while thou ſojourneſt heere, O my ſoule! ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in bodie, from that Lambe of <hi>GOD,</hi> thy Saviour; to thinke upon this <hi>IESVS,</hi> to ſpeake of this <hi>IESVS,</hi> to ſeeke this <hi>IESVS,</hi> to ſerue this <hi>IESVS,</hi> who hath called thee unto this honour, to bee the Childe of <hi>GOD;</hi> and ſo, to be a King for ever, to poſſeſſe fulneſſe of Ioye in <hi>GODS</hi> praeſence, and at His Right Hand Pleaſures for evermore.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXVIII"/> KNeweſt thou, O my Soule! how farre that bleſſed wiſe GOD, thy Father, hath advanced the fleſh of man; belieue me, thou couldeſt not offend, if I ſhould curſe thee, if thou attempted but ſo much, as to luſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5665:29"/>after thoſe evils, wherewith (alace) a verie world of people are nowe groſſelie defiled. And I could not but bee aſhamed to be offended, if thou ſhouldeſt curſe mee, if I ſhould preaſe to giue theſe members of my bodie, unto the committing of thoſe ſinnes, which thouſandes (alace) doe commit in this our time, even with delectation and greedineſſe. O my ſoule! hath not GOD honoured the fleſh of man verie farre, in making it to be a Cabinet, to lodge that immortal Soule, made by His Majeſtie, even of an Heavenlie ſubſtance? hath not our GOD more highlie advanced the fleſh of man, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to bee the Temple and dwelling place of His Holie Spirit? Yea, to be that Spirituall, Immortall, Incorruptible, and Glorious pleniſhing, which muſt fill and keepe the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens for ever? Yea, hath not His Majeſtie advanced it more than highlie, in His bleſſed and onlie begotten Sonne, IESVS, that holie One; being contented, to aſſume, and unite in one perſonall union with His Godheade, the verie fleſh of man: not onlie for a while, walking on earth, in that our nature, but tranſporting that our fleſh to the higheſt Heavens; ſo that Hee, who is GOD alwayes, aequall with the Father, and with the holy Ghoſt, is cloathed with the fleſh of man? And He who is cloathed with the fleſh of man, is GOD, aequall with the Father, and with the Spirit. ô Coeleſtiall Spirites, and heavenlie Angles! who ſerve your bleſſed <hi>GOD</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes readilie, faythfullie, buſilie, fullie, and joyeful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, can ye compare with that man, who by a liuelie faith, is ingraffed into that God-Man, and Man-God, IESVS? Would that holy One cloathe Himſelfe with your nature, ſo that you may ſay, He who is <hi>GOD,</hi> is alſo an Angell? and he who is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, is <hi>GOD?</hi> Or rather,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.</note> tooke Hee not the Seede of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham?</hi> ſo that the believing man may ſay, He who is GOD, is man alſo; Hee who is man, is <hi>GOD</hi> alſo. ô Coeleſtiall Spirites, ſaid that bleſſed <hi>GOD</hi> your and our Glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, ever of anie Angell, or to anie Angell, The angell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7.</note> My fellow? And yet our bleſſed <hi>GOD</hi> can (ſpeaking to, and of His Sonne, in whom we are thus beyond meaſure honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) ſpeake thus of Him, The man My fellow. Dareſt thou
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5665:30"/>then, ô my Soule! attempt to diſhonour this <hi>GOD,</hi> who hath ſo farre honoured thee? Yea, dareſt thou attempt to adviſe me, being kitled with anie deceiueable luſt, to abuſe this my fleſh, or anie member of it, ſince His Majeſtie hath ſo wonderfullie advanced it? We all thinke, that <hi>David</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawe himſelfe verie groſſelie, to <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> the creeple ſon of dead <hi>Ionathan,</hi> who proved conſtantlie rarelie kinde to <hi>David;</hi> when having tried the groſſe falſehood and ſeditious treacherie of that villane <hi>Ziba,</hi> hee ſaide to the poore creeple abuſed honeſt man,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.29.</note> 
               <hi>Haue I not ſayde, Thou and</hi> Ziba <hi>divide the landes?</hi> But when ſhall men, who holde themſelues for good Chriſtians, thinke and confeſſe, that they overſee themſelues, abuſing moſt groſſelie the <hi>LORD</hi> their <hi>GOD?</hi> when they crye aloude, albeit not with their ſhrill voyces, yet with their vilde workes, even to the hearing of that <hi>GOD,</hi> to whom they be more than oblieged in all reſpects, but chiefely for advancing their fleſh ſo highly, which is the onlie ground of mans whole foelicitie. <hi>O LORD GOD!</hi> haue I not ſaid, Thou and the Devill divide betwixt you? Offend not, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! that I ſpeake thus: for if manie, profeſſing <hi>CHRIST</hi> amongſt us, may bee believed when they ſpeake, they haue appointed their hearts for <hi>GOD;</hi> and yet if their lyves ſhall be narrowlie tryed, it ſhall be clearelie found, that they haue dedicated their fleſh, and ſo their eyes, eares, mouth, handes, feete, and that foule member of their bodie, for the Devill; for (alace) be thoſe their members imployed in the ſervice of anie, beſide the devils ſervice? Is this to bee thankfull to that <hi>GOD,</hi> who hath beene kinde unto them? Is this to honour <hi>GOD</hi> by their fleſh, who hath ſo honoured mans fleſh? Knoweſt thou not, ô looſe Chriſtian! that the Devill is the Accuſer of the Children of <hi>GOD, CHRISTS</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10.</note> Who firſt craftilie entyſeth them to ſinne againſt <hi>GOD,</hi> and then maliciouſlie accuſeth them before <hi>GOD,</hi> for ſinning againſt Him. Now, <hi>O!</hi> how fearefull an Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall this bee (hearken, hearken, ô my Soule!) when Satan thine accuſer, ô looſe Chriſtian! preſenting himſelfe before that great GOD, upon the ſight of thy looſe and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5665:30"/>lewde life; ſhall peartlie ſay, ô LORD, it pleaſed thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, out of thine unſpeakeable loue towardes man, to cloathe thine owne bleſſed Sonne with the fleſh of man; even to the ende, that in that fleſh He might ſuffer for man, and thereby to advance man to the higheſt Heavens, who having wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie made himſelfe my Companion, through ſinne, ſhould haue beene adjudged to the loweſt helles, with mee for ever: and yet, LORD, here is a man, yea, a verie world of men, who haue defiled themſelues, with abominable Idolatries, bowing their knees to the worke of mans handes, lifting up their handes, and ſending up their cryes, to baſe creatures; forgetting the great and bleſſed Creator; yea, defiled in their fleſh, with fearefull Blaſphemies, cruell Murthers, filthie Inceſts, Adulteries, and Fornications, with brutiſh Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Covetouſneſſe, and Oppreſſion. <hi>O</hi> LORD! will not Thy Majeſtie, being that juſt judge of the world, be avenged upon ſuch groſſe unthankefulneſſe, and adjudge with the ſoules the bodies of ſuch men, to that Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone, forevermore: ſeeing they haue ſo groſſelie ſhamed that their fleſh, which thou haſt ſo greatlie honoured? Thinke upon this, ô my Soule!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman.</hi> 6.12 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.3.4.5.</note> keeping thy ſelfe from all inward filthineſſe. Forget not this, O my Soule! but charge me alwayes, In GODS Name, to keep this my bodie, &amp; all the members of it, from all outward uncleaneneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXIX"/> EVen the filthieſt deboaſhed liver, O my ſoule! offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, when hee is compared to the Devill; and yet everie filthie liver, will treade the devils path. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the devill, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! peartlie praeſent himſelfe amonſt the Children of GOD, before GOD? And yet no ſooner goeth hee from His Majeſties praeſence, but hee can run with ſpeede, not onlie to overthrow all that belonged to that juſt man <hi>Iob;</hi> but alſo to bereaue him of his health: thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereby to make him blaſpheme GOD. Even the filthieſt liver offendeth, if hee bee called a <hi>Iudas:</hi> yet as <hi>Iudas</hi> went from his Maſters Table, to deliver Him into the hands of His Enemies; ſo manie, called Chriſtians, can take their Iourney, as it were, from <hi>CHRISTES</hi> Chamber, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5665:31"/>
               <hi>CHRIST.</hi> Alace, alace, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! howe manie bee there, who praeſent themſelues with <hi>GODS</hi> Sainctes, in <hi>GODS</hi> Houſe, before <hi>GOD,</hi> to heare His Word: and yet comming from it, deboaſh themſelues, in all uncleanneſſe? O! how manie bee there, who going to Prayer, and ryſing from Prayer, thinke never upon that which they haue confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or bound themſelues unto, while they were praying, till they goe backe againe to their Prayer; deboaſhing themſelues betwixt their one prayer, and their other prayer, even in thoſe ſame ſinnes, for the which in prayer they accuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they condemned themſelues, craving <hi>GOD</hi> pardon, and ſolemnlie avowing to abſtaine from them. The judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Charitie, which ſuſpecteth the beſt of all, adviſeth mee to thinke, that theſe knowne Murderers, Adulterers, Fornicators, Drunkardes, and ſo foorth, when they goe to their prayer, doe nowe and then, confeſſe theſe their ſinnes, craving pardon for them, and promiſing to amende their liues: and yet, with the Swine, even nowe waſhen, after they haue riſen from their knees, they can turne to the puddle of their wonted wickedneſſe. Let all ſuch then, who doe heare GOD ſpeaking unto them by His Worde, and who doe ſpeake to GOD by prayer, joyne repentance, with their hearing, and with their prayer: remembering, that he onelie is bleſſed, who heareth the Worde of GOD, and doeth it. And that the prayer of that man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 11, 28. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.9.</note> who draweth away his care from hearing the Law, is abomination before GOD.</p>
            <p>LET mee not bee carefull, ô my Soule! for my life, what I ſhall eate, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXX"/> or what I ſhall drinke: or for my bodie, what I ſhall put on: For thy bleſſed GOD, that Great Maſter-Houſe-holde of His Kirke, can wiſelie provide for His owne, even in their greateſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: albeit not alwayes that which they would bee at; yet ever that which ſhall ſerue them, untill His good worke bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in them. The King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> taketh Straw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which before was furniſhed unto them: the Taske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of <hi>Aegypt</hi> reſolue them, notwithſtanding heereof, that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5665:31"/>the number of their Britkes muſt bee fulfilled daylie. And when they, with wearie heartes, are carefull to provide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of Strawe, they can finde none:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodus,</hi> 5.</note> for the people of the Land will neyther giue them anie for requeſt, nor ſell them anie for Silver. How then ſhall they come by it? and where ſhall they finde it? Bleſſed bee GOD, ô my Soule! vvhen the King, vvho was a man carrying the ſame ſhape which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> carried, vvith his Taske-maſters, and people, can refuſe all helpe, unto diſtreſſed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> can adde affliction, to afflicted <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that ſenſeleſſe dead hard Earth, vvhich they trode upon, vvill offer her helpe unto them: praying them, as it were, to pull up her haire, before they ſhould periſh: and ſo ſhee propyned them with that Stubble wherewith ſhee was covered, before they ſhould want altogether that wherewith they might make Bricke unto cruell, blooddie <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> O <hi>David!</hi> no favour canſt thou finde, notwithſtanding of thine humble carriage, and manie good ſervices, in the eyes of <hi>Saul,</hi> thy maſter, and father in Law: and yet, art thou not lovinglie embraced, and kyndlie entertayned, by that ſtranger <hi>Achis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.</note> that uncircumciſed King of <hi>Gath? Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebel</hi> doe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeeke thy lyfe, O <hi>Eliah!</hi> but doe not the verie devouring Ravens entertayne it as carefullie? O <hi>Nebuchadnezar!</hi> thou art ſo fearcelie ſet againſt thoſe three Children of GOD,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.3.4.5.6.</note> who refuſed to worſhip that Image, vvhich thou madeſt, that thou vvilt not onelie haue them caſten into an hote fierie Fornace; but thou wilt haue this Fornace to bee hote at that one time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daniel,</hi> 3.</note> ſeaven tymes more, than it was wont to bee hote. Alwayes, vvere not theſe furious, fearce, fierie flames, mercifull unto them? Yea, ſo mercifull unto them, that not onlie they ſlew them not; but that the haires of their head were not burnt; neyther were their Coates chaunged, nor anie ſmell of Fire upon them. O abuſers of <hi>Davius!</hi> yee are ſo maliciouſlie ſet againſt the Servant of GOD, <hi>Daniel,</hi> that yee will haue him caſten into the Denne of Lyons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Daniel,</hi> 6.</note> becauſe hee prayed unto his owne GOD, as hee was wont, contrarie to that wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, vvhich yee, by your malicious ſubtiltie, made your king to ſubſcribe unto. And yet thoſe Lyons will haue him ſaved,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5665:32"/>whom yee reſolved to haue ſlaine. No refreſhment can hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie <hi>Lazarus</hi> finde, at the handes of the rich Glutton; and yet he can finde eaſe from the tongues of bloodie Dogges.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke,</hi> 16.</note> How manie wicked men, in this our time, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! haue ſoft Doane Beds, and Pillowes, to lye upon; while the Religious Childe of GOD, cannot finde a Feather Bedde, no, not a Fodder Bedde? and yet the Earth is contented, to be a Bed unto him. But, ô my ſoule! what if the cruell Princes of the Earth will not ſuffer, ſo much as this hard earth, to be a bedde unto thee? O, then! what ſhalt thou doe? what canſt thou looke for? be ſure, either this thy provident, pittifull, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full GOD, who hath abſolute commandement over all, ſhall (O my Soule) eyther alter their hearts, and make them pittie thee, or furniſh thee with a ſtrong contented heart, able to beare out all that they can deviſe, or doe, againſt thee; or make death, which is a cruell Burrio to the Wicked, but a loving friende to His ſecret ones; to finiſh thy Laboures, and to ſende thee to His Reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXI"/> IOyne, ô my ſoule! the thirtiefiue, and thirtieſixe verſes, of the twelft of <hi>Exodus,</hi> with the ſixt, ſeventh, and tenth verſes, of the fift Chapter of that Booke; that thou mayeſt learne, even with joy, to put on that Head-piece of Hope; poſſeſſing thy ſelfe alwayes in patience, confidentlie, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurelie, depending upon thy GOD; even when the King, vvhen the Task-maſters, vvho command under the King; yea, even when with the King, &amp; his Task-maſters, the whole People of the Land are ſet againſt thee, and buſied about nothing, but thine overthrow, and deſtruction. But vvherefore? but vvherefore ſhould I doe this, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule? becauſe He who hath the hearts of all men in His hands, can alter both Court and Countrey ſo, that, that man vvho this day, who this yeare, would neither grant thee for begging, nor ſell thee for Silver, a poore Sheafe of Straw, to make Bricke of, to thy King; will another day, another yeare, giue the willinglie, and freelie, all his Golde Chaines, all his Bracelets, all his Ringes; and ſo ſpoile himſelfe, to make thee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5665:32"/>rich. And vvould ye not thinke this a vvonder of vvonders? Liue there not manie this day, who having experience of this, in their owne perſon, may ſay, that that King, vvho ſometime vvas ſeeking mee, to haue offered my bodie to the Gallowes, mine head to the Axe, hath, ſince that, lovinglie embraced mee, graciouſlie accepted mee, to kiſſe his hand, and ſet mee higher than ever I was before? Haſt thou compared, ô my Soule! the ende of the third of <hi>Ester,</hi> with the ende of the eight of <hi>Ester?</hi> In the ende of the third of <hi>Ester,</hi> the Scrybes are writing Letters, the King is ſignating Letters, and the Poſtes are riding, and running, through the Countrey, with Letters. In the ende of the eight of <hi>Ester,</hi> the Scribes are wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Letters alſo, the King is ſignating Letters alſo, and the Poſtes are running, and riding, upon Horſes of Pryze, and Dromidaries, with Letters. Alwayes, tell me, vvhat Letters are the Scribes writing, is the King Signating, are the Poſtes carrying, in the ende of the third of <hi>Ester?</hi> And what Letters be thoſe which the Scribes are writing, the King is ſignating, the Poſtes are carrying, in the ende of the eight of <hi>Ester?</hi> In the ende of the third of <hi>Eſter,</hi> Letters are vvryting, ſignating, and carrying, by the Scribes, King, and Poſtes, to roote out, to kill, and to deſtroy, all the <hi>Iewes,</hi> both young, and olde, Children, and Women, in one day. In the ende of the eight of <hi>Eſter,</hi> Letters are vvriting, ſignating, and carrying, by the ſame Scribes, by that ſame King, by thoſe ſame Poſtes, who vvrote, ſignated, and carryed the former, granting the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in vvhat Cities ſoever they were, to gather themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ſtand for their liues; and to roote out, to kil, and to deſtroy, all the power of the People, and of the Province, that vexed them; both Children, and Women, and to ſpoile their goodes. Haſt thou compared, ô my Soule! the 19, 20, and 21, verſes, of the third of <hi>Daniel,</hi> vvith the 28, 29, and 30, verſes, of that ſame Chapter? In the 19, 20, and 21, verſes, fearce <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> is ſo furiouſlie ſet againſt <hi>Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah, Miſhael,</hi> and <hi>Azariah,</hi> and that <hi>GOD</hi> vvhome they worſhiped, that hee would haue them caſten into, and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the hote fierie Fornace. But in the 28, 29, and 30,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5665:33"/>verſes, pacified <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> thinketh ſo reverentlie of their GOD, and is ſo favourablie diſpoſed towardes them, that bleſſing their GOD, hee maketh a Decree, That everie People, Nation, and Language, which ſpake anie blaſphemie againſt their GOD, ſhould bee drawen in pieces, and haue their Houſes made a jaxe. And beſides this, hee promoted thoſe three, in the Province of <hi>Babel,</hi> highlie, whom hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed before to burne cruellie. We uſe to ſay, (and would to GOD our tongues were onelie accuſtomed with ſuch ſpeaches) Bleſſed bee hee who can make friendes of fremde folke. And vvhen I conſider this, O my Soule! I muſt ſay, Bleſſed be hee, who can make deare Friendes of deadlie Foes. Alwayes, what muſt thou doe, ô my ſoule! to the ende, thou mayeſt finde this to thy comfort, and benefite? Let that wiſe King <hi>Salomon</hi> informe thee, as he was informed by that true <hi>Salomon,</hi> the King of wiſdome: <hi>When the wayes of a man pleaſe the LORD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>he will make his enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> If thou haue compared, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! the 41 verſe, of the 27 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> with the 4 verſe, of the 33 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and with the 29 verſe, of the xxxv. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> thou ſhalt find this to be moſt true. In the 41 verſe, of the 27 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> I heare cruell <hi>Eſau</hi> avowing to ſlay his brother <hi>Iaakob,</hi> when the dayes of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for his Father ſhould come. Alwayes, not onlie ſee I this ſame <hi>Eſau</hi> in the 4 verſe, of the 33 of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> embracing this <hi>Iaakob,</hi> falling upon the necke of this <hi>Iaakob;</hi> but in the 29 verſe, of the thirtiefiue of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> I ſee <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iaakob</hi> moſt kindelie, as it became Brethren, burying their dead Father <hi>Iſaac.</hi> So great advantage reaped <hi>Iaakob,</hi> by walking before <hi>GOD,</hi> and amongſt men, ſo, that his wayes pleaſed GOD. If a Subject then find that he is wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged by his king, let him not doe that which may grieue GOD, and pleaſe his King; to the ende hee may obtaine his Kinges favour. If a Childe finde, that he is wronged by his Father, let him not doe that which may grieue <hi>GOD,</hi> and pleaſe his Father; that hee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Fathers favour. If an Husband finde that hee is wronged by his Wife, let him not doe that which may grieue <hi>GOD,</hi> and pleaſe his Wife; to the ende, he may obtaine his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5665:33"/>Wiues favour. If a Wife finde, that ſhee is wronged by her Husband, let her not doe that which may grieue <hi>GOD,</hi> and pleaſe her Husband; to the ende, ſhee may obtaine her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes favour: But let them all ſticke conſtantlie unto <hi>GOD,</hi> doing that alwayes, which is good in His Eyes: ſo bee ſure, that <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall eyther mooue King, Husband, Child, Wife, and ſo foorth, to doe that which they ſhoulde doe; or elſe ſtrengthen Subject, Childe, Husband, Wife, &amp;c. to beare out, with contentment, the greateſt wronges that can bee done unto them. Wilt thou not then, ô my Soule! loue this GOD? ſeeke this GOD? ſerue this GOD? with all men, and againſt all men, whether hee clappe thee, or kuffe thee; heale thee, or wound thee; quicken thee, or ſlay thee?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXII"/> TRue Saving Prayer, O my ſoule! may juſtlie be ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, That Royall Ambaſſadour, Prudent, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious: Who lodging alwayes in a cleane Cabinet, is directed, from that Greateſt King, towardes that Greateſt Monarch: and who can no wayes, upon anie condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bee mooved to ſtay, from journeying forwardes, till he come before Him, to whome hee was ſent: diſcharging that Commiſſion which hee carrieth in his Boſome: and, beſides Him, neyther to Mineon, nor Courteour, or anie of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectes, whatſoever. Tell mee, ô my Soule! can anie in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, anie under Heaven, teach thee to pray, to thy Salvation, beſides that Great King, even the Spirit of the Father, and of His Deareſt Sonne? And therefore, that Great Teacher of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> can reſolue thee thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman.</hi> 8.26</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit helpeth our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: for wee know not what to pray, as wee ought: but the Spirit it ſelfe maketh request for us, with ſighes, which cannot bee expreſſed.</hi> This Ambaſſadour of Prayer, comming from the Spirit, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lodge, but in the quickened Soule, and renewed heart, of GODS Childe. Reprobates, I confeſſe, may poſſeſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Delicates: but this Delicate, of Saving Prayer, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue. And therefore, the ſame Great Teacher of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> can marrie, as it were, Prayer and Salvation, after an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable manner together, ſaying:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever calleth upon the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5665:34"/>Name of the LORD,</hi> (to wit, being ledde by the Spirite of Adoption, the onelie Anker of Heavenlie Supplication) <hi>ſhall bee ſaved.</hi> Saving Prayer, beſides this, is ſo prudent, and couragious, that beeing ſent by this Spirite, from the honeſt heart of GODS renewed Childe, towardes that onelie Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-excellent Monarch, GOD, his Father, it will not giue ſo much as a looke, let bee a God-ſpcede, as it were, unto anie Angel, unto anie Sainct, in Heaven, unto anie Man on earth, (beeing ſo directed by that Spirit, by whome it was ſent) till it come in, before that Great Majeſtie of the GOD of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with whome onelie it hath to doe: and there, in His Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, powre foorth the ſelfe. O my ſoule! Art thou not thus charged, by GOD, thy Father?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15</note> 
               <hi>Call upon Mee, in the day of thy trouble.</hi> Art thou not thus charged, by GOD, thy Saviour? <hi>When yee pray, pray thus, Our Father, which art in Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.9.</note> &amp;c. Art thou not thus charged, by GOD, thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, thy Comforter, and Keeper? <hi>If anie man aske Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, let him aske it of GOD.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames,</hi> 1.5.</note> Search, ſearch, ô my ſoule! the whole Olde Teſtament, the whole New Teſtament, and trye, if there thou mayeſt forgather, eyther with Praecept, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thee to pray unto anie in Heaven, or under Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thy <hi>GOD:</hi> or, with anie Promiſe, That if thou prayeſt unto anie beſides His Majeſtie, thou ſhalt come ſpeede: or laſtlie, with anie practiſe, ſhewing thee, that ever anie of <hi>GODS</hi> Children, ever ſent up their Prayers, to anie, beſides that Bleſſed <hi>GOD,</hi> in whome they believed. Vnderſtande, underſtande, heerefore, O my Soule! that the ignorant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, vaine bablinges, of the blinde, ſuperſtitious Papiſtes, can bee no Saving prayers, indyted by the bleſſed Spirite of <hi>GOD:</hi> but windie, fooliſh, effectleſſe words, comming from their owne deceived Braynes, and fonde imaginations: For if they come from <hi>GOD</hi> His Spirit, they would bee dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto <hi>God</hi> onelie: but ſince they bee drawne up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to creatures, they cannot come from the true Spirite of that Creator, bleſſed for evermore: but from the lying ſpirites of baſe curſed creatures.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:5665:34"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXIII"/> THE blinde, blooddie, reſtleſſe Seminarie, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Earth to and froe, with Satan, ſowing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes where hee commeth (anie occaſion being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto him) his poyſoned, and poyſoning Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: eyther to impede the receiving, or to hinder the grouth, of the good Wheate of GODS Worde: to the ende, that hee may perſwade Man and Women, of all Rankes, even with ſome Greedineſſe, readilie to imbrace his lying Doctrine, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Invocation of Sainctes, hath verie highlie here-to-fore, and doeth verie farre as yet, advaunce that effectleſſe Compariſon, taken from the Courtes of Earthlie Kinges. And this Compariſon hee hath hatched, to the ende he may the more ſubtillie advaunce the Grandour, and augment the Wealth, of that Vylde Court of ROME. And with this, not onelie draw away poore ſimple people, from beeing truelie courteous with that KING OF GLORIE, Bleſſed for ever; but alſo to ſtirre them up (albeit hee abhorreth to confeſſe this) to kythe themſelues groſſe and avowed Traytors, againſt His Majeſtie. O ſhameleſſe Papiſt! Is not this thy fonde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeance, as Subjectes conſidering the Grandour of their Princes, and their owne baſeneſſe, are accuſtomed to goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Kinges, by Noble-men, and Courteoures; So the Children of <hi>GOD,</hi> conſidering the Excellencie of that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, wherewith their <hi>GOD</hi> is cloathed, beeing ſenſible in the meane time of their owne vildeneſſe, by reaſon of thoſe ſinnes, wherewith they are clogged, ſhould not attempt to goe to their GOD, but by thoſe Saincts, which bee in heaven. Hadſt thou, ô effronted Papiſt! hearkened unto that anſwere, now neareby twelue hundreth yeeres agoe, given to this purpoſe, by that famous Biſhop of worthie memorie, <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> thou wouldeſt haue beene affraid from kepping ſo greedilie, without anie ſhew or reaſon,<note place="margin">Ambroſe, on Rom. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> this effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe compariſon, &amp; from keeping it ſo pertinaciouſlie, even to this day, without anie kinde of ſhame. For this cauſe men and women, are mooved to goe unto Kinges, by Noble-men, and Courteoures, becauſe Kinges bee but men, and know not to whom they ſhould commit the governament of their
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5665:35"/>Countrey: but while a man hath to doe with his GOD, from whom nothing can be hidde, (for all men are knowne by Him) wee haue neede of no ſuch mediator, but of a devoate, humble, holie heart; for whenſoever ſuch an heart ſhall ſpeake, GOD ſhall loving lie anſwere it. But, <hi>O</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and deceiving Seminarie! to what purpoſe will this thy compariſon ſerue thee, in that countrey, where the King, with whom thou haſt to doe, hath, by a ſpeciall Edict, under His great seale, and publicke Proclamation, raiſed thereupon, authorized His eldeſt Sonne, to bee the onlie Mid-man, by whom all His Subjectes, great, and ſmall, anie wayes offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Him, or ſtanding in neede of anie thing from His hands, ſhould haue recourſe unto Him; diſcharging them herewith, under all higheſt paine, to make anie ſure by the mediation of anie other whomſoever? Secondlie, if the Prince, the Kinges eldeſt Sonne, beeing thus authorized by His Father, haue by his publicke Proclamation (having received ſpeciall warrand from His Father to doe ſo) certified all His Fathers Subjectes, That none of them can poſſiblie come to His Father, but by him. Thirdlie, if the Lordes of the Kinges ſecret Counſell, beeing certified of the trueth hereof, would beſide this (being commanded by the King, and His Sonne) charge all the Subjectes, to come to the Kinges Sonne, yea, to His Sonne onlie, whenſoever they haue to doe with the King His Father? Now, <hi>O</hi> blind, peart Seminarie! I appeale thy conſcience, unleſſe thou haſt lay de aſide all conſcience, and made that Whore of <hi>Babel</hi> thy god; if thou be acquainted with that voyce which was ſounded from the Heavens, that day, in the which that bleſſed, and ſole Saviour of the world, was baptized, <hi>This is My welbeloved Sonne, in whome I am well pleaſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.17.</note> Yea, heareſt thou not this voyce ſounding over againe, with an addition, that day in the which that holie One was transfigured? <hi>This is My welbeloved Sonne, in whome I am well pleaſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>heare Him.</hi> ô Seminarie! wilt thou not heare the Sonne, ſaying unto thee; <hi>I am the Way, the Veritie, and the Life:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>no man commeth to the Father, but by Mee?</hi> Heareſt thou Him not thus ſweetelie inviting thee to come directlie unto
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5665:35"/>Himſelfe? <hi>Come unto Mee, all ye which are wearie, and ladened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28</note> 
               <hi>and I will eaſe you.</hi> Yea, <hi>O</hi> Seminarie! poſſeſſed with a deafe devill, when GOD ſpeaketh to thee, by His Worde: wilt thou not heare that great Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the whole counſell of GOD, ſaying unto thee, <hi>There is one</hi> GOD, <hi>and one Mediator betwixt</hi> GOD <hi>and Man; even the Man CHRIST IESVS?</hi> Sure I am,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> were olde <hi>Chryſostome</hi> aliue, hee would as farre condemne the avowed, prophane, madde follie, of the ſuperſtitious papiſt in this point, as hee commended the holie wiſedome of that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Woman, whoſe Daughter was poſſeſſed with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: for ſpeakes hee not thus, touching her? <hi>Beholde the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>of the woman: ſhe prayeth not to Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſost. de Cananea.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe maketh not her ſupplication to Iohn, ſhe goeth not to Peter, neither reſpecteth ſhe the companie of the Apoſtles, requiring helpe from any of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but inſtead of them all, (taking happily unfained repentance for her companion) ſhe goeth directly forward to bleſſed</hi> Ieſus, <hi>that only Well which was able to yeeld out that ſweet Water which ſhe thirſted for.</hi> But will the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Seminarie reſt, ô my ſoule! when theſe things are broght from the verie Mouth of GOD, unto his eares? No, no, for the tricking Seminarie, who can cunninglie catch ſimple ſouls by his intrapping ſubtilties, will confeſſe, that bleſſed <hi>IESVS,</hi> that onlie Sonne of the Great King, is the onelie Mediator of Reconciliatſon betwixt <hi>GOD</hi> and Man: But, with this, he will maintaine, That there be other mediators of Interceſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Him, who may make, and doe make, requeſt unto <hi>GOD,</hi> for us. Spare not, ſpare not here, O my Soule! to ſay unto the ſhameleſſe peart Seminarie, while hee ſpeaketh thus, Avoide, Satan, as one ſent foorth by that craftie Foxe, and cruell Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, firſt, by his ſubtiltie, to ſnare thee; &amp; then, by his crueltie, to ſlay thee: demaunding him, even from a ſtrong heart, and with a good countenacce, thus, O Seminarie! out of what booke, out of whoſe mouth, learnedſt thou to put a difference betwixt the mediator of Reconciliation, and the mediator of Interceſſion? For out of GODS Booke, out of GODS mouth, ſpeaking to thee by Scripture, thou learnedſt it never: albeit no booke, beſides GODS Booke; no mouth, beſides GODS
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5665:36"/>Mouth, muſt in this point informe thee, direct thee, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand thee. For telleth not GODS Booke mee, and ſo GODS Mouth, firſt, that wee haue no mediator, who can poſſiblie intercede for us at the hands of our GOD, but that Mediator who hath reconciled us unto GOD? For be not theſe the words of <hi>Paul? There is one God, and one Mediator betwixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.</note> If <hi>Paul</hi> had ſpoken thus, There is one Mediator betwixt God and Man, the man Chriſt Ieſus; hee had ſpoken enough to convince the lying Seminarie: but he wil ſay more; even thus, <hi>There is one God, and one Mediator betwixt God and Man, the Man Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> to make the Seminarie aſhamed (if hee could be) of his ſubtiltie. For hereby he would tell thee, ô my ſoule! That as there is onelie one true God, and no wayes, in anie reſpect, another, even the Father, Sonne, &amp; holie Ghoſt; ſo there is onlie one true Meciator, and no wayes, in anie reſpect, another. Secondlie, telleth not Gods Booke, and ſo Gods Mouth, mee, That this Ieſus Chriſt could not poſſiblie haue bene a Mediator of Interceſſion for us, praying to God for us; unleſſe Hee had bene a Mediator of Reconciliation for us, by His blooddie Sacrifice, ſatisfying His Fathers Iuſtice for our Sinnes? O vilde Seminarie! dareſt thou giue that great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple (whome Ieſus loved, and who lay in Ieſus Boſome) the Lie? And yet ſpeaketh he not thus? <hi>If anie man ſinne, we haue an Advocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt, the Iuſt: and He is the Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for our ſinnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.1.2</note> Thus joyntlie joyning Chriſts Interceſſion and Reconciliation together, and from His Reconciliation of us, proving, That He hath onlie right to intercede for us: for if He had not reconciled us, He could no wayes haue had any intereſt to pray for us; neither durſt we haue had attempted, to haue had recourſe to Him, as to our Mediator. Yea, which is more, O my ſoule! if He had not bene our only Reconciler, He could not haue bene our Mediator at all. Let me not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ô my ſoule! heare anie more word touching <hi>Maries</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, anie whiſper touching <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> and ſo foorth, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and of Saincts interceſſions: for were anie of theſe cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for me? hath anie of theſe reconciled my God to me? but let mee heare alwayes my bleſſed and onelie Ieſus: let mee ſee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5665:36"/>Him: let mee imbrace Him: let mee kiſſe Him: yea, let mee keepe Him, while I breathe, in the inward Coffer of my heart, as mine onlie Mediator, who hath reconciled me to God, who intercedeth for me with God: for mine eyes haue ſeene, mine eares haue heard, mine hands haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, that ſweeteſt ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sacrifice, offered up by Him, upon the Croſſe, unto God His Father, for all my debt of ſinne, and of puniſhment, due unto mee for my ſinnes. And this His Sacrifice I haue ſeene, heard, and handled, in that cleane and cleare Looking-Glaſſe of Gods Worde, and in that ſhining Mirrour, of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, annexed by His Majeſtie unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXIIII"/> I Muſt confeſſe, O my Soule! that thou canſt not but bee much mooved, when conſidering Gods Fatherlie direction plainelie given to thee, when weighing Gods Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſes clearlie made to thee, thou askeſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.7.8.</note> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt not; ſeekeſt, but findeſt not; knockeſt, but haſt none to open unto thee: for as then Satan cannot but preaſe to take ſome advantage of thee, ſo thou canſt not but at the firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering this, bee much amazed. Alwayes, ô my Soule! I muſt charge thee, not to murmure (ſo much as in ſecret) againſt thy good God, albeit Hee appeare not to heare thee when thou calleſt unto Him. Yea, I muſt command thee, not to attempt, to ſuffer that loue, wherewith thou art oblieged, alwayes to loue thy good God, aniewayes to waxe colde, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it His Majeſtie deferre to grant thee that which thou haſt bene craving: yea, albeit He denie altogether to giue thee that which thou haſt bene long ſeeking: yea, which is more, albeit He put into thine hand, and lay upon thy backe, that which is flat contrarie, unto that which thou haſt beene, even for manie dayes, with manie ſighes, having thy knees bowed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Him, and thine handes lift up unto Him, deſiring Him to giue thee. For I muſt tell thee, O my Soule! that the frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lookes of God thy Father, are more pleaſant to the ſight of his well ſchooled Childe, than the ſmyling of all living can bee unto Him: that the hand of God thy Father, taking from his owne, that which the blinde worldling accounteth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5665:37"/>onlie to be profitable for him; yea, that the hand of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, laying that upon the backe of His owne, which the dead worldlings account onlie hurtfull to them, is even then more kinde, more liberall unto him, and more mercifull towardes him, than the handes of all living, being opened wide, to giue them liberallie, to clappe them kindlieſt that poſſiblie can bee. Till this world ſhall ſtand, thoſe comfortable Oracles ſhall alwayes bide inviolablie true, <hi>The Eyes of the Lord are upon the Righteous; and His Eares are open to their cryes. The Lyones doe lacke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.15.16. <hi>Roman.</hi> 8.28</note> 
               <hi>and ſuffer hunger: but they which ſeeke the Lord, ſhal want nothing which is good. All thinges worke together for the best, to them that loue God.</hi> And ſo, ô my Soule! I muſt aſſure thee, that thy God, cannot but alwayes heare thee, but alwayes helpe thee: for He heareth thee, either ſo, that Hee granteth thee that which thou craveſt, as thou craveſt it; or as good as thou craveſt; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not that ſame which thou wouldeſt be at; or a better than that is which thou thinkeſt onlie to bee beſt. <hi>Anna</hi> maketh a ſute to her God, and is heard, as ſhe craved; for as ſhe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red foorth her ſoule before God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.</note> for a ſonne, ſo ſhe receiveth a ſonne from God. <hi>Paul</hi> cryeth over, and over, to God; alwayes that ſame which he craveth, is not granted him, and yet that which was as good is not refuſed him:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.8.9.</note> for while he beſought his Lord, that the angell of Satan, which buffetted him, might depart from him, hee is not fred from that angell, but Gods Grace is made ſufficient for him, to make him ſtand under that aſſault; and in ende, to triumph valiantlie. <hi>David,</hi> a man according to the heart of God, dealeth with his God moſt earneſtlie by prayer, by teares, and by faſting, for the life of that childe which <hi>Bathſeba</hi> bare unto him, alwayes, that is not granted; for that childe died: nevertheleſſe, a better is given unto him: for was not that wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> who built a Temple to God, borne afterwards, of that ſame <hi>Bathſeba,</hi> unto him? for if that childe had lived, according to <hi>Davids</hi> ſute, being begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by him upon her, while <hi>Vriah,</hi> her Husband, was aliue, would hee not haue lived alwayes as a manifeſt note of <hi>Davids</hi> Adulterie, and Murder, and ſo bene caſten up unto him, by prophane people, who could eaſilie grippe his ſinne, but no
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5665:37"/>wayes conſider his repentance? Forget not, O my ſoule! that comfortable Oracle, ſounded by thy Maſter, and Saviour, <hi>What man is there amongst you, who if his ſonne aske him Bread, would giue him a Stone? or if he aske Fiſh, will hee giue him a Serpent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>or if he aske him an Egge, will he giue him a Scorpion?</hi> And ſhall thy God, ô my Soule! even the God of my ſpirit, who is more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and wiſe than the father of my fleſh can be, if I craue that which Hee accounteth to be a Stone, albeit, I account it to be Bread; which he accounteth to be a Serpent, albeit I eſteeme it to be a Fiſh; which He accounteth to be a Scorpion, albeit I account it to be an Egge? Thou ſeekeſt the Bread of Honour from God; and He knoweth, that if thou hadſt Honour, thine Honour would proue a Stone, to diſhonour Him, and ſlay thee; and therefore, He refuſeth to giue it. Thou craveſt the Fiſh of Health, and Wealth, from God: but he knoweth, that Health and Wealth, would proue a Serpent, to bite thy ſoule, unto death. Thou wouldeſt bee at the white Egges of ſweet Pleaſure: but Hee knoweth, that they would proue a biting Scorpion, to hurt thee: and therefore Hee denyeth them to thee. Thou abhorreſt ignominie, and ſhame before men, as an hurtfull Stone: but God knoweth, it will be Food, and Bread to thee: therefore Hee covereth thee with it. Thou abhorreſt Sickneſſe, Povertie, Impriſonment, Baniſhment, inward Temptations, outward Croſſes, yea, Death it ſelfe, as byting Serpents, and Scorpions, able to ſlay thee: alwayes, thy God knoweth, that even thoſe be the only ſavoury &amp; ſweet Fiſhes, and Egges, which are able to ſaue thee: and therefore He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneth thee with them. Forget not, O my ſoule! that ſweet ſpeach of <hi>Augustine,</hi> ſubſcrybing unto the trueth of theſe three comfortable alleadged Oracles: <hi>Bonus Dominus qui ſaepe non tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit quod volumus, ut magis attribuat, quod malimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augustine,</note> O! how good a Lord is our Lord! who oftentimes giveth us not that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, which wee would haue; to the ende Hee may graciouſlie giue us, that which wee rather ſhould haue craved. <hi>Bernhard,</hi> embracing <hi>Augustine</hi> in this point, can ſay to thee ſweetlie, O my Soule! <hi>Saepe multos Deus non exaudit ad voluntatem ut exaudiat ad ſalutem.</hi> Our God oftentimes refuſeth,<note place="margin">Bernhard,</note> to heare manie of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5665:38"/>His owne, according to their will; to the ende, Hee may heare them for their weale. But heare, <hi>O</hi> my Soule! leſt thou deceiue thy ſelfe; thinking that thou haſt right to the hearing eare, to the pitiful heart, to the helping hand of thy God: &amp; ſo, that He heareth thee, that Hee pitieth thee, and that at length Hee will helpe thee: howe mayeſt thou bee aſſured, that thou art even then heard of Him, pitied of him, and that thou ſhalt receiue helpe from Him; even when in appearance thou muſt thinke, that He heareth thee not at all? Hearken, hearken, <hi>O</hi> my ſoule! findeſt thou Grace, while thus thou art uſed, by thy wiſe, piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, to continue in praying unto Him, while He refuſeth, as thou thinkeſt, to heare thee? Haſt thou Grace, to deſire, to continue in praying unto Him, while Hee delayeth (as thou thinkeſt) to heare thee? Yea, which is more, findeſt thou the ſmalleſt meaſure of griefe, becauſe thou canſt not deſire to continue in praying unto Him, as thou wouldeſt? that thou canſt not pray unto Him, as thou ſhouldeſt? Bee aſſured, that God, whom thou thinkeſt to be farre from thee, is neare thee, is with thee, yea, is in thee, by His Spirite, as in His Temple: hearing thee, albeit thou heareſt not that He heareth thee: pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying thee, albeit thou feeleſt not that He pitieth thee: and for to deliver thee, albeit thou thinke, that thou canſt not bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Anſwere me, anſwere me, ô my ſoule! if thou canſt, If thy God heard thee no wayes, pitied thee no wayes, and were never to helpe thee, couldeſt thou deſire to be heard of Him? to bee pitied by Him? to bee helped by Him? Yea, if thy good God longed not, as it were, to doe thee good, couldeſt thou eyther long, or lament, that thou longedſt not for good at His hands? For, as he who never ſaw the Sunne, cannot miſſe the ſight of the Sunne; ſo, hee who never ſawe God, cannot miſſe God. Thus it is not nature that miſſeth Grace, but Grace which miſſeth Grace onlie. And therefore, he ſpake truelie, who ſaid, <hi>Num oranti beneficia denegabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
               <hi>qui orantes at ne deficiant ſua pietate inſtigat:</hi> Can that good God refuſe to grant His Gifts unto that perſon, who praying unto Him for them, is ſtirred up, by His Goodneſſe, not to faint, but to continue in praying unto Him.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:5665:38"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXV"/> THou canſt not be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ô my ſoule! being acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with holie Scripture, that as cruell <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> had fearce Taske-maſters, ſet by him, over the Lords <hi>Iſrael;</hi> So that cruell Dragon, Satan, thy greateſt Enemie, hath his owne bloodie Taske-maſters, ſent foorth againſt Gods ſecret ones, to ſhame them, to ſlay them: and that thoſe his Taske-maſters reſemble, in one thing eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie, the Taske-maſters of <hi>Pharaoh. Pharaohs</hi> Taske-maſters, as holy Scripture teſtifieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exodus,</hi> 5.13</note> are not contented to intimate <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> will, unto the poore <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> but they muſt, with fearce countenances, ſharpe tongues, &amp; ſtrong handes, haſten them, without all delay, to doe it: Even ſo, Satans Taske-maſters, doe not onlie command thoſe, over whom they are ſet, and in whom they doe reigne, to obey the Devils will: but they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten them ſo to obey it, that they can neyther eate, nor drinke, nor ſleepe, as it were, till Satans will be executed by them. But who be the Taske-maſters of Satan, ô my Soule? Let that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, whome Ieſus loved, and in whoſe Boſome hee lovinglie ſometime lay, reſolue thee: <hi>The luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 2, 16</note> 
               <hi>and the pryde of life.</hi> Young <hi>Ammon</hi> is ſo boaſted, and beaten, by that Taske-maſter, <hi>The luſt of his fleſh,</hi> nighing after his ſiſter <hi>Tamar,</hi> that he pyneth away, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.</note> till having obeyed the command of that fearce, filthie Taske-maſter, he defile his ſiſter unnaturallie. Young <hi>Abſolom</hi> is ſo beaten, and boaſted, by that alluring Taske-maſter, <hi>The pryde of lyfe,</hi> longing after a Crowne, that he can take no reſt, by night, nor by day,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> till hee put even the Crowne off his own olde father, upon his head: contenting, that his father, in the meane time, for ſafetie of his lyfe, flee out of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> bare-headed, and bare-footed. That uncouth Traytor, <hi>Iudas,</hi> is ſo boaſted, and beaten, by that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Taske-maſter, <hi>The luſt of the eyes;</hi> and ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.14.15.</note> of Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that he cannot be ſtayed poſſiblie, by all that his Maſter hath done to him, by all that his Maſter hath done for him, by all that his Maſter hath ſpoken to him, in the audience of his brethren, touching him who ſhould betray Him; from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying of Him: and all to the ende, that hee may ſee thirtie pieces of Silver delivered unto him. Lament, lament herefore,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5665:39"/>O my Soule! the miſerable eſtate of theſe: pitied by others, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not by themſelues, who eſteeme themſelues to bee the greateſt amongſt men. Will Noble men, will great men, bee commanded, by that Great Good God, ſpeaking unto them, and haſting them to doe His Good Will, by thoſe His kindly, ſmyling, and meeke Taske-maſters, in whoſe mouthes Hee hath put His Worde? And yet they dare bee contented to bee commanded by, and to bee (as moſt miſerable ſlaues) couched under that Evill one, Satan, and thoſe his furious Taske-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: haſting them to doe the Devils evill will. Will our Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-men, O my Soule! be ſervants to anie man? content to bee Schollers? to bee Trades-men? to bee Crafts-men? And yet they can rejoyce to ſuffer themſelues to be abuſed by Satan, &amp; by Sinne; by the which in ſuch ſorte hee fighteth againſt their Soules, that no ſlaue roweth in a Galley ſo farre againſt his will, under the uncouth bondage of that cruell Monſter, the <hi>Turke;</hi> as a very world of theſe men, in this our Age, row with both their hands, and feet, as it were, under the Devil: haſtned in the meane time, by his foreſaide Taske-maſters: and yet not againſt their will, but willinglie: not with griefe, but with joy. Let the Adulterer, the Idolater, the Murderer, the Fornicator, the Drunkard, the Seditious man, the Oppreſſor, the Falſe man, the Covetous man, lay his hand to his heart; ſo ſhall hee finde this to be true. The conſideration hereof, made wiſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> (acquainting us with the nature of the wicked man, and counſelling us, to beware of him) thus to ſpeake, <hi>Enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of the Wicked, and walke not in the way of evill men: avoyde it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.14.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>goe not by it: turne from it: and paſſe by it: For they cannot ſleepe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they haue done evill: and their ſleepe departeth, except they cauſe ſome to fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXVI"/> HAth thy God, ô my ſoule! ſweetlie this day ſounded in thine eares, the ſoft voyce of Conſolation; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing unto thee comfort, deliverie, and His beſt things: be not offended, if to morrow thine eares be made to heare the ſharpeſt ſound of the bitter winde of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, threatning thee with greater troubles, and griefes, than
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5665:39"/>ever thou heardeſt, or felt before. O <hi>Iaakob!</hi> hath not thy God propined thee liberallie, with the Birth-right?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.29.</note> enriched thee gloriouſlie, with His bleſſing? but muſt thou not heare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, that <hi>Eſau,</hi> thy Brother, hath avowed to kill thee? whereupon thou muſt be contented, not onlie to turne thy backe upon thy tender Parents; but with paine and griefe, to ſerue a churliſh <hi>Laban,</hi> for twentie and one yeares. O <hi>Ioſeph!</hi> ſeeſt thou not to day thy Brethrens Sheaues ſtanding up, and doing reverence to thy ſheafe? but muſt thou not be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, even after that, to ſee thy Brethren ſtripping thee naked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.</note> of thy partie coloured Coate? and thereafter, firſt, putting thee in a Ditch, and then ſelling thee to the <hi>Midianites,</hi> to bee carried downe to <hi>Aegypt.</hi> O diſtreſſed <hi>Iſrael!</hi> heareſt thou not <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Commiſſioners of thy God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.29.30.31.</note> to day ſweetlie telling thee, that they were ſent of God to bring thee out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> that thou mighteſt celebrate a Feaſt to the Lord thy God, in the Wilderneſſe? Alwayes, muſt thou not bee contented, the next day, to heare <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his Taske-maſters, ſpeaking thus to thee bitterlie? <hi>Thus ſayeth</hi> Pharaoh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>I will giue you no more Straw: goe your ſelues, get you Straw where you may finde it; notwithſtanding the number of Brickes which you made in time paſt, ſhall not be diminiſhed.</hi> O <hi>David!</hi> telleth not <hi>Samuel</hi> thee,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.27.</note> that thou ſhalt be a King of <hi>Iudah?</hi> yea, anoynted he thee not with Oyle, in the Name of the Lord, to certifie thee hereof? Alwayes, after this, muſt thou not be contented, not onlie not to finde a nightes lodging in thine owne houſe; but not ſo much as a Caue, or hole, to hide thy ſelfe in, in all <hi>Iudea</hi> and <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Thus he, who to day heareth bleſſed Ieſus, who is Loue it ſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing unto him a Crowne, muſt be contented to morrow, to haue wiſe Ieſus ladening him, with a Croſſe. But, O! wherefore dealeth our wiſe God with His owne thus? For ſpeciall graue reaſons, ô my Soule! is this done, I aſſure thee: for hereby He tryeth the faith, the hope, the patience, of His owne: hereby He ſtirreth them up, earneſtlie to deale vvith Him, by continuall Prayer: for He will haue His owne to aske that from Him, which He is to giue unto them: yea, this He doeth, to moue His owne, being ſet at libertie, to be the more
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5665:40"/>thankefull; and to uſe Gods good thinges beſtowed on them the better: to make the Wicked, His, and their, unjuſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the more inexcuſable; and to conquiſh the greater Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to His owne Name: when having, in ſpight of all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, performed that liberallie, which Hee did promiſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlie to His owne, He advanceth them, and overthroweth His, and their enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XXXVII"/> LEt it not grieue thee, ô my Soule! that ſome day, hid up from thee, that in ſome place, unknowne to thee, thou muſt lay downe this duſtie tabernacle, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt for ſome yeares bene cloathed, as with a Garment: but ſee that thou, (being now happilie ingraffed in Chriſt, and through His grace dying to ſinne daylie, for the which He died:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23.</note> and living to Him, who died for thee, and roſe againe) even with an holie languor, (ſubmitting al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thy will to the good will of God) long for that day, with that great Apoſtle. And when that day ſhall draw neare, I charge thee, ô my ſoule! that in that day, thou lift up thy ſelf, &amp; rejoice. What wiſe man, being wearied all the day long, with laboures abroade, will grieue to draw home at night? Firſt, to refreſh himſelfe with ſome entertainment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, laying aſide his Garmentes, to goe to his reſt: knowing, that ſo (pleaſing God) when the morning ſhall ariſe, hee will finde his Garment againe. And dareſt thou, O my Soule! bee grieved, when that night of Death ſhall approach, all thy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Labours ſuſtained by thee here being finiſhed, to lay down this thy clay bodie, and to haue thy ſelfe conveyed by thoſe Angels of God, unto that refreſhing Palace of that Paradiſe, which is Aboue, nowe wyde open to keepe thee, becauſe of the obedience of that ſecond ADAM, who died for thee? Yea, dareſt thou, O my Soule! be grieved, in that night of Death, to haue this clay bodie conveyed, to that reſting Bedde of the Graue, ſweetelie nowe perfumed, by the Buriall of the Sacred Bodie of thy gracious Saviour IESVS? For knoweſt thou not, when that glorious brightlie ſhyning Morning of Iudgement ſhall approach, in the which that Mightie GOD, thy Saviour,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5665:40"/>whom the Heavens doe now containe, ſhall manifeſt Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Glorie, accompanied with thouſands of His Angels, and with the ſound of the laſt Trumpet, that thou ſhalt not onlie meet with that wonted Garment of thy Bodie; but take it up againe, but put it on againe? Alwayes, not as men take up their Garments here in the morning, after their reſt in the night: but farre otherwayes, more comfortablie, joyfullie, and profitablie, by a thouſand, thouſand degrees. As men here lay aſide their Garments at night, going to their reſt, ſo they take them up in the morning: &amp; having taken them up, they goe foorth againe, eyther to their wonted, or ſome new labour. But I muſt tell thee, O my Soule! to thy great comfort, That thou ſhalt take up this tabernacle of my bodie, in that ſhining Morning of Iudgement, in a farre more excellent eſtate, than it was laide downe into by thee, into that darke night of Death, and when it was laide downe in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Graue. It was laide downe in corruption, it ſhall be taken up in incorruption: it was laid down in diſhonour,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42 43.44.</note> it ſhal be taken up in glorie: it was laid down in weaknes, it ſhal be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up in power: it was laid down natural, it ſhal be taken up Spiritual. Could this be well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, O my ſoule! would I ceaſe, while I liue here, to imploy all the members of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die holilie? And, when Death ſhould approach mee, would I not undoubtedlie be heartfullie contented, even with joye, to lay down this earthlie tabernacle? Again, I will aſſure thee, O my Soule! (becauſe ſo hath my Lord and Maſter, IESVS, by the ſweeteſt words, of His owne ſweeteſt Lippes, aſſured me) that thou, having, in that day of Iudgement, taken up, and put on, that Garment of this Bodie, ſhalt never goe foorth, to anie olde, or new Laboures againe: But ſhalt alwayes reſt, in end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe reſt, for evermore; free of all ſuſpition of future griefes: and filled with a verie Sea of unexpreſſible Glorie. For in that day, thou being happilie praeſented a chaſte Virgine, well dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and trimmed,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</note> with the Ornamentes of thy Glorious Husband, IESVS, before thy Glorious Husband, IESVS, ſhalt haue that Marriage nowe contracted with Him, joyfullie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized, and perfectlie conſummated. And then, thy Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5665:41"/>Husband, having wyped away all Teares from thine eyes, ſhall take thee in to His moſt ſecret Cabinet of Glorie: there, not onelie to ſee, but to poſſeſſe for ever, that Glorie, vvhich Hee poſſeſſed before the Worlde was made. Could this bee well weighed by thee, O my Soule! wouldeſt thou not crye with <hi>David? As the Hart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ayeth for the Rivers of Waters, ſo panteth my Soule after Thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>O GOD: My Soule thirsteth for GOD: even for the living GOD. When ſhall I come, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the praeſence of GOD?</hi> Yea, wouldeſt thou not crye with <hi>Paul? O wretched Man that I am! Who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mee from this Bodie of Death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>I deſire to bee looſed, and to bee with CHRIST, which is best of all.</hi> Yea, thou wouldeſt unceſſantly crye with the Kirke, CHRISTES Bryde, <hi>Come, LORD IESVS:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>Even ſo: Come quicklie. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
